<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Essayes or rather, Encomions prayses of sadnesse: and of the emperour Iulian the Apostata. By Sir William Cornewallis, the younger knight.</title>
            <author>Cornwallis, William, Sir, d. 1631?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840809</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1346:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Essayes or rather, Encomions prayses of sadnesse: and of the emperour Iulian the Apostata. By Sir William Cornewallis, the younger knight.</title>
                  <author>Cornwallis, William, Sir, d. 1631?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe, for Richard Hawkins, and are to be sold at his shop in Chauncery lane, neere Seriants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Julian, --  Emperor of Rome, 331-363 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:1"/>
            <p>ESSAYES <hi>Or rather,</hi> ENCOMIONS, <hi>Prayſes of</hi> SADNESSE: AND <hi>OF THE EMPEROVR</hi> IVLIAN the Apoſtata.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Sir</hi> WILLIAM CORNEWALLIS, <hi>the younger Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> for <hi>Richard Hawkins,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Chauncery lane, neere <hi>Seriants</hi> Inne. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thoſe precepts that aduiſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of the infirmities of the mind, haue bin euer more ſafe and ſweet, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs that like laws hold their peace vntil they haue them in their power, and then plucke them vp by the roots: iſ he that preſcribes temperance be the beſt Phyſicion: hee the beſt Pilot that foreſees a ſtorme: he the best Stateſ-man, that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the dangers of his Countrey in their bud and greenneſse: and in a word they the happiest Counſellors, that ſeeke to keep vs out of the contingency of perill: it is not impoſsible (Reader) but I may be of ſome vſe to thee: But I prayſe <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> ſo doth the Phyſicion his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which howſoeuer thy taſte abhorres, thy reaſon deſires, and being once downe, thou art content to forget the lothſomneſſe, and regard the operation. I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my preſcription to thee no further, then that it cannot hurt; what good it may doe, let thy experience reſolue thee; which the warranty of the ſafety may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite thee to: If it wants thoſe graces and embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he hath need of, that aduentures on an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation; let a plaine true tale be accepted better then a
<pb facs="tcp:178005:3"/> filed falſhood; eſpecially ſince through the cloud of mine Ignorance truth ſhewes thee light enough, to direct thy way, though not to delight thee in thy iourney: I ſeeke not honour from thee, nor am I the ſubiect of thine opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thy cenſure ſhall onely concerne thy ſelfe: for mee, though I ſhould hold my cloake the faſter for the winde; yet ſhall I neuer yeeld it to the Sunne; he that feeles not their preſent power, needes not feare the future, and I am armed againſt both, either with a knowledge or a dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of proofe: And ſo I leaue thee to thine owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if thou haſt one; or if thou haſt not, to liue like the Moale by hearing: <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:3"/>
            <head>THE PRAYSE OF <hi>SADNESSE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that haue bleſſed their time with drawing into their owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes the conſideration of the world and her mutabilities; and kept them there, to ſtrengthen their reaſon againſt the vanity &amp; waywardneſſe of their affections and paſſions, know already, I may offend opinion, but not truth, vndertaking as impertinent a worke, as he that intended to prayſe <hi>Hercules:</hi> to theſe I addreſſe not my ſelf, vnleſſe they wil pleaſe to perfect me, ſince I cannot them. But to thoſe I am directed, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſmyles of Fortune haue depriued of the true knowledge of the condition of man, or youth hath not yet ripened; or ſuch vulgar and earthly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whoſe iudgement dazeled with beholding the outward ſplendor of Fortunes Minions (the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt of all) cannot or will not ſee with what terrible cares and diſcontentments, the purple robe is lined.</p>
            <p>I know, but feare not, the danger of cheriſhing and defending ſo vnwelcome a gueſt as ſadneſſe; ſo ſhunned, ſo abhorred: For ſince I am well aſſured,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:4"/> they haue condemned rather her countenance, then her ſelfe: and that both her Iudge, Iury, and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, hath bin that acrie monſter <hi>Opinion;</hi> that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all vpon truſt, and anſwers nothing with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; I was the rather inclyned to be her friend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>opinion</hi> was her enemy; the firſt proofe of her goodnes,<note place="margin">The firſt proofe of her goodneſſe.</note> ſince ſhe is hated, by ſo falſe and obſtinate an enemy to wiſdome and Iudgement.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, becauſe our humane weakneſſe, and chiefely thoſe that I deſire to inſtruct, vnderſtand beſt by contraryes; as health is beſt knowne by ſickneſſe, plenty by want, it is fit I ſhew them what mirth is made of: and ouer what a troupe ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; that beholding her, and her band diſrobed and anatomized, wearie and aſhamed of the ſight, they may by putting off their preiudicat obſtinacies, be made firſt hearers, and conſequently obeyors, of a worthier conductor.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What Mirth is.</note>That mirth is a naturall quality of mans, I deny not, but withall, I think it one of thoſe that he hath little cauſe to boaſt of; it is true that he makes mirth and ſadneſſe the ballance of his affections and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and is wayed by them: thus hee accounts his winnings and loſings, and the ſame is expreſſed in ſadneſſe or mirth: but whether moſt of theſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed winners, are not rather betrayed, then ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; looſened, diſordered, and corrupted; then ſtrengthned, grounded, &amp; inſtructed, I think there is no man that hath well obſerued himſelfe, and his paſſages conſiderately, but will affirme. Who can doubt of this, that knowes the ſlightnes of her compoſition? children make her of babies, and hobby-horſes: yong men of ſports, hawkes, horſes,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:4"/> dogs, or worſe: old men of riches, Stateſmen of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorers, honour, and aduancement; Women of gay clothes, many louers, and flattering glaſſes: it is one God they adore, though worſhipped in ſeuerall ſhapes: and though the difference amongſt them makes them deſpiſers of one anothers choice; yet to the vnintereſſed beholder, they play al at one game, though not all for one ſumme. <hi>Et que veneraris et quae deſpicis, vnus exae quabit cinis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee haue touched the ayme, and end: Let vs now ſee the purſuers and adorers of mirth; and they that make her the goddeſſe of their actions, a people either ſo light and imperciptible, as nothing can come beyond their ſenſes: or ſo opinionatiue and obſtinate, or rather ſo drunke with pleaſure, as they will not knowe, what they may and muſt: or a third ſort, that clap myrth between them and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, for feare of corraſiues, that keepe her vp like a ball, and run after her, to bee the further off from themſelues, who might know, though <hi>Vinum, cantus, ſomnus, commot iunculas illas primas, non raro ſanarunt irae doloris, amoris at nunquam aegritudinem, quae radices egit et fixit pedem,</hi> to caracterize theſe further then in generality, were needleſſe: for what ſhall the picture need, where the originall is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? with what other are brothell-houſes, and Tauerns ſtuffed? <hi>Voluptas, humile, ſeruile, imbecillem, caducum; cuius Statio et formices et popinae ſunt,</hi> what are the inhabitants of theaters, meetings, feaſts, try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, but ſuch as either acknowledge no God ſo willingly as Mirth and Pleaſure; or ſuch as dare not come home into themſelues, for feare of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and miſcarriage?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:5"/>
            <p>In the meane time, O poore reaſon, at how baſe a price art thou ſold? Or art thou but a name with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an eſſence? Or a broken Reed that the will of man dares not ſtay it ſelfe vpon, for feare of falling? Or els what a blue-eyed choyſe is theirs, that for the moſt idle, momentary, and ſicke effects of mirth, and pleaſure, impawne not onely their time, (which is vnredeemeable) but themſelues, which they thinke too well ſold to repurchaſe.</p>
            <p>But now it is fit I haſten to them, who ſeeke not mirth, but are ſought of her: for ſuch is the luſt of Fortunes benefits, as whileſt the body feeleth her ſelfe able to purchaſe her deſires, and to gorge her ſenſes, ſhe abandons herſelfe to all ſenſualities, and reioyceth in her owne fulneſſe: to you then, vpon whom none but fayre winds haue euer blowne in this careire of your ſuppoſed happineſſe: can you ſee for all your high and ouertopping places, your end and reſting place? Or are you not rather the arrowes of the Omnipotent arme, that are yet flying, not at yours, but at his marke: and are no more owners of your owne purpoſed ends, then you were guilty of your owne beginnings? In the meane time effeminated with your proſperity, and as it were ſtill ſucking vpon the breſt of Fortune, if ſhe turnes her backe and retires, how miſerable doth ſhee leaue you? Still bleating after the teat, and like thoſe nice creatures, that become tame with taking their bread from others hands, vnable to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to your ſelues the leaſt helpe or comfort.</p>
            <p>Wee doe ſee that Nature and all her producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſupport them and her ſelfe by inceſſant chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and reuolutions; generation and corruption
<pb facs="tcp:178005:5"/> being to the earth like riuers to the ſea, in a reſtleſſe current, and perpetuall progreſſe: doe wee ſee the flouriſhing and falling, not only of Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but of Kingdomes and Commonwealths, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Trophies, and whatſoeuer the vaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man hath contriued for the ouercomming of time? and can we vpon ſome ſmall remnant of Fortunes bounty, thinke to eſtabliſh a perpetuity of mirth and pleaſure? No, no, he that takes not this time to prouide for a world, and in the midſt of his pleaſures doth not thinke how fraile and tranſitory they are, will pay dearely for his iollity; when ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by death, or ſome diſaſter, they leaue him in an inſtant, ſo much more miſerable then others; as he hath depended vpon ſuch vncertainties: without which, his life is moſt lothſome vnto him, and with which, death moſt fearefull and abhorred.</p>
            <p>But to what end is all this tendred to the adorers and louers of mirth? Their heads and hearts are all ready filled with their own delights: which muſt be conſumed by affliction, before the precious balm of Sadneſſe can either enter or worke. <hi>Fabius</hi> ſaid, he feared more <hi>Minutius</hi> victories the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouerthrows: which may be rightly applied to the generall diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of man, his ſucceſſes infecting him with an ignorant confidence, intoxicating his reaſon with preſumption and oſtentation, which are ſuch dayly effects of worldly proſperities, as they that thinke themſelues Lords, are often the vnworthieſt ſort of ſlaues: and their opinionatiue happineſſe, the moſt wretched miſery: not vnlike the madde <hi>Athenian,</hi> that imagined himſelf poſſeſſed of al, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed he was true honor but of his own diſtemper &amp; lunacy.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:6"/>
            <p>To young men there belongs more pitty, aſwell becauſe nature hath her hand in this their thirſt of pleaſure: they beeing yet by the heate of bloud, and the quickneſſe of their ſpirits, and the ſtrength of their ſenſes, iolly and gameſome: as alſo that it muſt be time, and the wounds and skars, gotten by their wretched careleſneſſe, that muſt make them capable of aduice: ſince (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayth) their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paſſions and pleaſures ſet ouer them, more cruell and tyrannous Gouernours, then thoſe that had the charge of their minorities: now who is it that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this diſtracted dance, of youth, but mirth? for whoſe ſake and pleaſures they are inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: what is irregular, indiſcreet, vnlawfull, diſhoneſt; nay, what lawes, either of mans natures, or Gods, are in theſe apprehenſions, ſtrong enough to containe them within their bounds? <hi>Galba</hi> in his adoption of <hi>Piſo,</hi> amongſt his other prayſes ſayth; you whoſe youth hath needed no excuſe: a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſo rare and glorious, as there needed no more to illuſtrate his name and fame to all poſterity; for who els, vnleſſe fettered and chained with nature or fortune, but in their firſt wearing the freſh gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of youth, haue not ſoyled and ſpotted it; as their whole life after (though painefully and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly directed) hath not bin able to wipe out their faults, and refreſh the gloſe of their reputation? hence it is, that <hi>Delicta inuentutis meae &amp; ignorantias meas ne memineris Domine,</hi> is taught by all, and vſed by all; ſo ineuitable a diſeaſe is youth: of which we need no witneſſe, ſince euery mans conſcience doth iuſtifie it; the generality and antiquity, hauing made it veniall: and by conſent, we bind none from theſe
<pb facs="tcp:178005:6"/> ſlips and ſtumbles, but old men and and women: the reſt paſſe the muſters ſo farre from checking, as they produce many of their follies as the markes of ſpirit, and generoſity: and by their will would make of an old vice, a young vertue: who can hope now to deliuer this flouriſhing ſeaſon of youth, from theſe Caterpillers? ſince mirth and pleaſure allures; opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on animates; and community hides them from the ſight of themſelues and actions: this it is that makes nothing more currannt, then to pay one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our faults, and no man truſts ſo much to his owne vertue, as to his neighbours or Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vices; wee repoſe our ſelues in the defect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and no man ſtriues further, then to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely good: we aduance our ſelues vpon ruins, and thinke our ſelues well, becauſe another is worſe: O lame ſhift! O drunken remedie! I will then ſay but this, to thoſe young men that will heare me, Since you know not the way to true happineſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment; ask not of them that are yet in the race; but of them that haue paſſed it: propoſe vnto your ſelues ſome patterne to imitate, <hi>(niſi ad regulam prauam non corrigas)</hi> and to ſtrengthen your iudgements, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thoſe that haue already acted their parts: take one of theſe admirers of mirth and pleaſure; and an other that hath euer made his reaſon the taſter of all his actions: and compare theſe together, and then chuſe which of them you would be: there cannot thus farre off bee ſo corrupted a iudgement, as not to know the beſt; the difference is then a little time, <hi>&amp; hoc quod ſenectus vocatur, pauci ſunt circuitus amoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Behold then the match, for a few yeeres to boote, this vicious hatefull perſon is taken, that deuoured
<pb facs="tcp:178005:7"/> his owne honour and reputation: and with his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſwallowed euen his very ſoule, and that liues now but in his infamy: rather then that well ordered ſpirit, that hath left a true and perfect circle of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet gouern'd life and death, and left the world heire of many rich and worthy examples: who in this conſideration, but muſt crie out with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>O what is man, that thou art ſo mindfull of him, &amp;c?</hi> or why hauing taken our iudgements thus hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſhould wee reply vpon it? carrying vs through the world; that in our entrance hath thus ſtumbled and fallen: he hath then the firſt ſigne of recouerie, that in this his beginning miſtruſts his owne wayes; and dares offer his wounds to the Surgeon: it is an incurable ignorance, that dares not put it ſelfe to mending. <hi>Plato</hi> would haue offenders repaire to the Iudge and Magiſtrate, as to the Phyſicions of the ſoule, and ſubmit themſelues to puniſhment, as to the medicine of recouery, but this was too high an imagination for practiſe; yet thus farre we may goe, and vpon the ground; and not in the ayre: hauing, vpon a due examination, found it fit to miſtruſt our ſelues, it followes euen in common reaſon, not to throw our ſelues raſhly into any action: but to aſſiſt our weakneſſe with gaining conſideration time: this diſarms our paſſions of their violence, for their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being out of heat, and neuer going but running, being once ſtayed, and ouertaken by reaſon, they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter willingly ſubmit themſelues vnto her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are eaſily managed: It is an axiome in Philoſophy, that our firſt motions are not in our owne power: which is true no longer then we liſt: for he that will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke himſelfe, without a pauſe and deliberation,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:7"/> diſſolues the Acrimony of his affections; and makes them of the cruelleſt Tyrants the moſt profitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. It is true, our ignorance and ſloth make eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing terrible vnto vs: and we wil not becauſe we dare not, and dare not becauſe we will not: this makes vs ſubmit our ſelues to any thing that doth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flatter or threaten vs: and like ſome ſottiſh weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that giue the reines of their gouernment, into the hands of their wiues or ſeruants; thinking then they buy their peace, when they ſell it: thus do they grow vpon vs, and by compoſition, not force, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come maſters of the place; being iuſt ſo ſtrong as we are weake. The ſcouts of <hi>Antigonus</hi> relating vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the multitude of his enemies, and aduiſing by way of information the danger of a conflict, that ſhould be vndertaken with ſo great an vnequality: he replied, And at how many do you valew me? In this ciuill wars of our ſelues the firſt diſorder and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our ouerthrow proceeds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a falſe valuation of our owne ſtrength: we are content to imbrace our owne true naturall worth, ſo wee may haue leaue to yeeld our ſelues to ſome furious paſſion or ſoothing affection: but would we now take a true knowledge of our owne valew, we might eaſily redeeme our ſelues: God and nature haue not dealt ſo tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with man, as to giue him charge of that he cannot hold: if we loſe the game it muſt be by play: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince we are likely to bee beſieged by the world, and her allurements; leſt famine or treaſon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, let vs turne out of the walls, all vnprofitable pleaſures; and knowe betimes that mirth becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neither the fortune, nor condition of man: ſo is hee enuironed with dangers, and ſo ſubiect
<pb facs="tcp:178005:8"/> to intrappings, <hi>omnis vita ſupplicium eſt,</hi> there is no day, houre, or moment, that brings a certaine ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of armes: but to the contrary, our life is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall war-fare, repreſenting vnto vs inceſſant dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and perils: wherefore wee muſt alwayes ſtand vpon our guard, and keep a ſtraight watch vpon our ſelues; not only examining the humors that goe in and out, their arrants, and pretences: but euen euery motion and thought; for of ſo many different pieces is the little world of man compounded: ſo ſtirring, ſo infatigable, ſo full of changes and counter-changes, ſo ſodainely eleuated, as ſoone deiected: and in a word, ſuch a compoſition of contrarieties; as he that doth not continually obſerue himſelfe, and ſteddily fixe his eyes vpon all his actions; ſhall ſodainely grow a ſtranger to himſelfe, and be vtterly ignorant of his owne proceedings: if this then be a time for mirth, we may eaſily imagine; who doth not alone call all the parts and faculties of man from their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and charge, to feaſt and glut themſelues with ſenſualities; but returneth them ſo corrupt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baunched, as like <hi>Hannibals</hi> army, after their winte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>Campania,</hi> they cannot bee knowne for the ſame men; ſo haue they melted their courages with delicacie, and with ryot made themſelues impatient, and almoſt incapable of diſcipline. To conclude, ſuch is the weakneſſe of man, and ſo ſtrong are his bodily inclinations, as if he doth not diuert or breake the force of his affections, reaſon alone is not able to reſiſt them: wherefore as <hi>Plato</hi> allowed old men, mirth and wine, to reuiue nature almoſt tyred in her long iourney, and to refreſh their ſpirits benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the coldneſſe of their dwelling: by the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:178005:8"/> reaſon, it is forbidden youth, whoſe bloud being now at the hotteſt, by the leaſt addition, or increaſe, falls into the diſeaſes of exceſſe, the moſt violent and vnreſiſtable extremes: wee ſee then it is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed but for a medicine, and by the difference of the conſtitutions of young men and old, it can bee no more wholſome for the one, then dangerous for the other: howſoeuer ſince it is preſcribed medicinably, the too frequent vſe, muſt either deſtroy the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or leaue onely the malignant quality aliue and vncorrected, vnto thoſe whom the out-ſide of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune dazels and allures, there is nothing to be ſayd by way of aduice; being ſuch, as neither nature, nor education hath fauoured, but are left to act the baſe and illiberal parts vpon this ſtage of the world: this is the multitude, the vulgar, the people that are bought and ſold, and reckoned by the hundred and the thouſand, and beare no price ſingle and alone; a madneſſe it were then, to thinke to moue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them together, when our Sauiour that fedde 5000. of them, and as many heard him, could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the admirableneſſe of his miracles, nor the excellency of his doctrine preuaile with them all, and returne them all beleeuers: this were ſufficient to deterre mee euen from but touching vpon this quick-ſand, were they not the harbour of opinion, where ſhee is ſtill reſcued from the louers of truth: neither is it impoſſible that ſome, yet of her and their party, vpon a truer information may forſake and bee aſhamed of their ſtation, or to be a piece of the body of this great Beaſt.</p>
            <p>There is nothing can enter into conſideration more ſtrange and improbable, then to ſee euen the
<pb facs="tcp:178005:9"/> moſt actiue and vnderſtanding ſpirits, to refer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their proceedings to the multitude, to eſteeme themſelues at their price, exceeds their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories and powers of ſatisfaction. The young man that thought to eſcape the being ſeene in a Tauerne, with retiring further into it, was iuſtly reprehended for going further in: but ſuch is the nature of vice, it hath an alluring looke, and a detayning tayle, our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires firſt allure vs to things vnlawfull, and when we are there, our feare bars vs in; but if euery man knew how much more right he might haue from his owne tribunall, if he will freely and ſincerely giue his reaſon her owne power, and how iuſtly an vnabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed conſcience will proceed, and how ſweetly and ſecurely he ſleeps, that hath receiued from them his <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> he would for euer diſclaime the cenſure of opinion; and with <hi>Phocion</hi> miſtruſt himſelfe, becauſe the people prayſed him: <hi>erubuit quaſi peccaſſet quod placuerit:</hi> and as the Prince of morality aduiſeth, <hi>Non reſpuit quid homines turpe iudicent aut miſerum,</hi> not it, <hi>qua populus; ſed vt ſcidera contrarium mundo i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intendunt, ita hic aduerſus opinionem omnium radit:</hi> but thus far had I gone out of the way, had I not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued opinion.</p>
            <p>To come now neere our purpoſe, in examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, circumſtances are not neglected, if they any way conduce to the end of our inquiry: thus Iudges and Magiſtrates make their vſes &amp; aduantages of names, and countenances, though it be impoſſible to make either ſo much as acceſſary: firſt then we finde, that <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> hath euer beene receiued as a witneſſe of truth; as <hi>In Sadneſse</hi> amongſt honeſt men, is taken for an infallible aſſeueration: whereas mirth hath ſo
<pb facs="tcp:178005:9"/> little credit, as when raſhneſſe or falſeneſſe hath made an eſcape, by the tongue, the refuge is to lay it to mirths charge: who as a licenſed Buffone, hath often leaue to paſſe the bounds of modeſty &amp; truth: againe, mirth is ſo like drunkenneſſe, that they are at this day, but as two names of one thing, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, meanes drunke, and drunke merry: whereas ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber expreſſeth a diſcreet temper, to rayſe and deiect themſelues at the pleaſure of their breathes, to take warrant from their countenances: and in a word, to liue and dye at their appointments: when ſingle, they ſcorne and deſpiſe them, and thinke euen their beſt thoughts ſcarce worthy of their foot-boy, yet the patterne and piece differeth not; and any one as farre as ſufficiency expreſſeth the whole, as Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſay of the diſeaſes of the body that are, and the ſame may come from different cauſes: ſo this of the mind, which proceedeth either from the laying their ambitious hopes vpon popularity, or ſuch as guilty of their owne intentions, dare not put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon the tryall of their conſciences.</p>
            <p>A third ſort there are, that feede, and cloath, and talke, and walke, and haue deliuered themſelues and their behauiour to bee brought vp by <hi>Opinion;</hi> theſe ſince they cannot be ſeparated from the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, neither can be, nor are worth the ſingling: for thoſe that Ambition hath perſwaded to this popular folly, they are worthy to bee deceiued: and were it not, that in all inordinate deſires reaſon is firſt van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, they could not but know; this beaſt is tame but in fayre weather; they loue that part of you which they vnderſtand, which is your fortune, loue and friendſhippe begins in the ſoule, and ends in the
<pb facs="tcp:178005:10"/> body: and theirs begin in the body and ends in the fortune: the two lignaments that tie the men to a iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and <hi>decorum</hi> in all their actions, are wit and honeſty; which they being defectiue in, can no more loue truely; then hee can ſpeake that is borne dumbe. Wherefore further then commiſeration, and the common duties of humanity, it is a madneſſe to be popular: for as they ſay, the chiefe ſtrength of the Lyon lieth in his tayle, ſo theirs in their mouthes; which as it deuoures all you giue, ſo they goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pay for all they take. It is true, <hi>Vbicunque homo eſt, ibi beneficio locus ect:</hi> thus farre charity commands, and further is ridiculous, or dangerous, or both: in Princes vnto whom they belong as a charge, and who hath power to make them feare, if they will not loue, popularity is no vice, but a part of vſe, and as dangerous for them to neglect, as for a priuate man and a ſubiect to follow and affect.</p>
            <p>We haue nothing more common and in practice amongſt decayed beauties, banquerouted by time or accidents, then to hide it from others eyes with art, and from their owne with falſe glaſſes: no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is it with them, that from the reflection of <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> behold the ſtate and condition of their minds; ſurely hee is afraid to heare truth, that dares not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of himſelfe: it is againſt our wils, if we tranſport to forraine eyes, or eares, any wares that are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall, or at leaſt formall: they are in the darke, and viſible but to our ſelues, that are fit for reformation: and as we know beſt their begettings and births, ſo are they the naturall ſubiects for our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to worke vpon: it is long ſince receiued, that in one, and the ſelfe ſame man, there may be a good
<pb facs="tcp:178005:10"/> man, and an ill Citizen; men and lawes take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of vice, no farther then their owne intereſt: diſeaſes that threaten but one, are oppoſed but by one, they are contagious and infectious, that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by generality. They then that goe to <hi>opinion,</hi> to knowe the temper and diſpoſition of their minds, go to the market, rather to ſell then to buy: and loue better to paint the walles and outſides of themſelues, then to rectifie and repaire their inward errors and defects: but farre worſe it is with them that dare not come to tryall, where their facts and actions are knowne, which is at home: is not this like children, which ſhunning the reprehenſion and chaſtiſements of one fault, multiply it to many? Or like the careleſſe debtor, that ſuffers the intereſt to outgrow the principall? How truely doth this proue the cowardiſe of vice, or rather the ſottiſhneſſe, ſince he conſiders not, that as faſt as hee runs from feare, the ſame haſte he makes to deſperation, where they ineuitably end, that neuer reckon with themſelues, till the ſumme vnimpeached by drinke or any other exceſſe?</p>
            <p>For the continuance, what men carry more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt before them, then thoſe, that haue worne out the ſobrietie of an honeſt looke, with a continuall girning or laughing? a marke of natures, ſo ſeldome failing, as it is in euery obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> held, for an irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable defect either of wit or honeſtie: of ſuch ſtuffe are commonly flatterers, time-pleaſers, &amp; faunguiſts made: people ſo obnoxious to vertue and worth, as were it not that they breed &amp; liue only vpon the luſt of Fortune, it were impoſſible to keepe them from a generall extirpation. For it is they that haue berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:178005:11"/> greatneſſe and riches of innocency, and made it of a dead and indifferent inſtrument in the power of the diſpoſer, to haue hatched more monſters then all the broode of vices beſides: and in a word haue been the viſableſt and chiefeſt procurers of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy ſentence of our Sauiour againſt rich men; that it is eaſier for a Camell to paſſe through a needles eye, then for a rich man to enter into the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>In the contemplating <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> and mirth, mee thinks, I ſee the true formes of the two Ladies that offered themſelues to <hi>Hercules,</hi> at his entrance into the way of the world, Vertue, and Pleaſure, the firſt with a ſettled compoſed countenance (not vnlike the South ſea) full of peace, certainty, and truth: no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruling paſſion diſordering or raiſing the leaſt bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, or moouing the ſmalleſt breath of perturbation: the other like a ſhop that ſets out the beſt wares to the view, and offers many pleaſing morſels to the ſenſes, and at the firſt ſeemes to reſemble bounty it ſelfe in freeneſſe and ſweetneſſe; but alas, ſhe is too ſoone wonne to be conſtant, ſhee brings not in your reckoning, til you haue conſumed what ſhe ſet before you, and then you ſhal know they are too deare, when it is too late to refuſe them: her ſmiles and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are like the ſun-ſhine daies of winter, ſtorm-breeders: her cleereneſſe, warmth, and calmeneſſe, produce euer cloudes and tempeſts; repentance, griefes and anxieties of the ſoule; and as Phiſicians hold, a continuall requiring ſtomake an infallible <hi>Symptomie</hi> of a corrupt and diſeaſed body: ſo may be ſaid of the louers of Mirth, that paſſe from one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to another, and dare not let their braines ſettle,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:11"/> leſt they ſhould ſee their owne deformities, their corrupted manners and the leproſie of their minds.</p>
            <p>Hitherto <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> hath gotten but a preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and hath but prooued her ſelfe better then a worſe; not approoued her owne goodneſſe: it is now time, to diſplay her in her owne excellency, not ſuch a one as reuerts all things vpon it ſelfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards no quality that returnes not laden with profit; but ſuch a communatiue goodneſſe, as growes not poore by imparting; but redoubles it owne ſtrength, riches, and ſplendor, with lending, aſſiſting and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it influence on others: but before I offer her, and her qualities to the view, it is neceſſary I deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher her: <hi>Philopamen,</hi> for want of an interpretor, was ſet to cleaue wood by his hoſteſſe, for his owne entertainment: the eye is a nice, buſie &amp; vndertaking ſence, if reaſon or iudgement prepare not her way.</p>
            <p>I meane not then, vnder the name of <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> to defend effeminate bewailings and lamentations; let them a gods-name, that ſubiect themſelues to this weakeſt impatience, be alſo ſubiect to the <hi>Lycian</hi> law; that bound theſe kind of lamentors to be arraied like women; nor am I an approuer, of a ridgid, ſowre, moroſe auſterity, ſince it is ſeldom other then the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſard of enuy, or vain-glory: ſuch were <hi>Nero</hi> his Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, <hi>nec deerant qui voce vultu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> triſti inter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectamenta Regia ſpectari cuperent:</hi> neyther is it a ſmall motiue to their condemnation, that the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and inquirer after vertue is deterred, to ſee her diſciples ſo ouer-clowded and drowned in heauines: rather like the followers of a Funerall, then her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and beloued, whoſe power and bounty doth not alone extend it ſelfe vnto all deſeruers, but
<pb facs="tcp:178005:12"/> makes all liues, fortunes, and accidents, not alone tolerable and to bee indured; but ſweet, wholſome, eaſie and oft times glorious, and exemplare: neither will I prayſe a ſorrow, that as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſayth, eates his owne heart; that abandons the rudder in a ſtorm, and dares not liue for feare of dying.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men know, it is the condition of humanity to be toſſed with contrary winds, and thoſe are the ſeaſons of diſtinction between wiſe men and fooles: euery man lookes gayly in a holiday fortune, but to be baſely ſet by, and to ſhine through an obſcure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, illuſtrates the riches and pretiouſneſſe of the mind: man hath not the throwing of the dice, but the playing of the caſt: he is Lord ouer his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the other part reacheth vp to heauen: where ſucceſſes and effects are deliuered backe, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the appetite of man, but the inſcrutable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and vpon that wee ought to reſt our ſelues, not onely with patience, but with comfort; that the onely fountaine of knowledge hath taken it into his owne hands, of whoſe better diſpoſing, it were the greateſt impiety and infidelity to make the leaſt doubt or queſtion: but it is ſadneſſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares vs for the acting of this and the reſt of our life truely; and as we ought: who muſt not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be of the diſcent of <hi>Niobe,</hi> ſtill labouring in teares and exclamations: nor a vaine-glorious or enuious Philoſopher, that bigge with his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, labours to proclaime it in his lookes: nor a ſilent fretting ſorrow, that will needs marry his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions:<note place="margin">A true deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> whoſe portrature I would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the generall ſtate and nature of man, hath drawne her ſelfe into an habite or poſture; in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:178005:12"/> places fit to reſiſt the incurſions of her enemies: in others to diuert them, and ſometimes like a wiſe Conquerour; making them of the cruelleſt foes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured friends or louing ſubiects: her outſide is ſober, calme, conſtant, modeſt, and for the moſt part ſilent; her inſide full of peace, induſtry and reſolution.</p>
            <p>To reduce theſe into a ſhorter and ſounder way, what knowledge, art, or ſcience is there, more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and important, then that which is wholly deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ordering of our life? this doth <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> moſt aptly and effectually: firſt inſtructing, then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orning, and laſtly, gouerning the life of man, with ſo much tranquillity, certainty, and happineſſe, as if we will truſt either reaſon or example, we ſhall find no liues to carry ſo continual a contentment as theſe: nor none ſo often, and ſo continually miſcarry as the contrary.</p>
            <p>Since then in theſe are comprehended the whole courſe of mans life, we will draw the picture of <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> within this compaſſe: ſo ſhall I not prayſe her more then profit my Reader: or if I faile, an vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Painter may ſpoyle a picture, but not a face; which a worthier vndertaking, may purchaſe glory, by the ſpoyles of my imperfections: ſince it is not then with man, as with other creatures, that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the greateſt part of their vnderſtanding, at the very entrance into the World, which being bounded and limited within a ſelfe preſeruation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no further then to a preſent conſideration of them and theirs: as it is a naturall propertie infuſed rather into their being, then into them; &amp; rather to the profit of nature, and her conſeruation, then for their particular benefit: as at the firſt it is ſtraight, and
<pb facs="tcp:178005:13"/> narrow, ſo time ripens it not, nor dilates it: farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it is with man, whoſe reaſon growes with him, and whoſe iudgement (as not compatible with his youth) is deliuered vnto him when he comes to age: at leaſt his minority is but the ſeed-time: in his Autumne comes his harueſt, that is the time of his inſtruction; this of vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Women enemies to true <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </note>Now, whether it be from the pride of man, that loues not to looke ſo low as his infancy, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt he hath to impart his time to a poore lumpe of fleſh, or that ſince Nature hath forced him vpon women, he thinks to turne the imperfections of time vpon the imperfections of Nature, and that they are fitteſt to breed &amp; hatch their puling wayward weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: whether from one, or from all, or from ſome more hidden cauſe: certaine it is, that to the moſt men in particular, &amp; to the common-wealth in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, there ariſeth great loſſe, by ſacrificing theſe their firſt yeeres, vnto their tuitions: from hence it comes, that when Poets would ſet vp a marke for imitation, they durſt neuer truſt a woman, ſo much as with their nurſing; but borrowed of their imagination, either a Goddeſſe or a Nymph, or rather then faile, a meaner creature. Some Philoſophers would allow them, no more intereſt in our conception, then to receiue che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, foſter, and re-deliuer vs: but alas, the large por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the imperfections that we inherit from them, aſſures vs the contrary: but ſince it is ſo much; as time, reaſon, inſtruction, and whatſoeuer the wit of man can apply, can neuer vtterly expell; hardly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, or temper: what a ſtupid careleſneſſe, raignes ouer the world, to increaſe our defects, by inlarging their time of gouernment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:13"/>
            <p>But neither to offend them, nor ſtay further from my ſubiect; their diſpoſitions will not take the rich colour of <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> which euer yeeldes that tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity &amp; ſettledneſſe of mind, that can propoſe the end, and proſecute the way, without diuerſion, or error: at leaſt, without thoſe that diſioyne our intentions; and ouerthrow our purpoſes: wheras (the very ſprings of paſſions &amp; affections) take &amp; change their forms, at the pleaſure of euery repreſentation, not vpon a deliberated iudgement; but according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation and concluſions of their ſences.</p>
            <p>Thus when we may ſee the power of <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> for inſtruction; ſince they that want it, are not to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with education, yet not to leaue enemies behind vs, though I wiſh we might obſerue their order, that ſet wild birds egges, vnder thoſe that are domeſticke and tame, to alter their wild condition into their fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-mothers more milde and familiar: and ſo could wiſh our dry nurſes were men, &amp; ſuch as could teach them words made of reaſon, as well as winde; and though there be many ſeuere, (if not malicious) cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures giuen vs, by our forefathers, againſt them in all ages, and by all countries, and by all profeſſions; of which infinit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>currence of cenſures, I will giue but one inſtance, <hi>nelle coſe di conſiglio in vna d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nna, e ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace di poterlo dare ne meno di pigliarlo per ſe e tanto p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ggio da teneclo ſecreto mat;</hi> yet doubt I not, but they are owners of ſuch perfections, as bounded, and kept in their owne circumference, are of much vſe and pleaſure: and they are to be honoured by vs, no leſſe then our mother earth, from whom wee no ſooner come, but wee ſtriue to returne againe: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſince we cannot be without them, it is great
<pb facs="tcp:178005:14"/> reaſon, they ſhould be entertained with a due reſpect: which is rather ſweetly, then ſeriouſly: let them haue their owne intereſt religiouſly anſwered; and for more, ſince it but corrupts them, and ſhackles vs; whatſoeuer old men and mad men doe, or haue done; wiſe men for their ſakes, will attend their charge, with more circumſpection.</p>
            <p>If then we deſire to frame a man that ſhall deſerue his being, and to be maſter of himſelfe and time: let vs begin betimes, to ſet ſuch Gouernours ouer him, as may both by their examples, and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dayly reflect vpon him, and infuſe into him the grace, and moſt inſtructiue influence of <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> for by this meanes hee liues fortified againſt the grand corrupter of youth <hi>Pleaſure:</hi> and the violent enemy of Age, <hi>Griefe.</hi> Surely the beame that keeps the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of man euen, is none other then <hi>Sadneſſe:</hi> for hee that thinkes to buy his peace with accumulating riches, or to be too ſtrong for fortune, with making himſelfe powerfull, doth but apply an outward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for an inward diſeaſe: which though it may ſometimes eaſe, ſeldome cures: but <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> that keepes vs at home, daily ſhewes vs the brittle frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all exterior things (which makes vs like an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my peſtered with too much carriage, neither fit to fly nor fight) vnites our inward powers, defends our reaſon, from the vapours and miſts of our affections; and ſtanding betweene the extremes of mirth and ſorrow, is the onely perfit moderator of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane actions. Cato, though he had many learned ſlaues, would not commit the education of his ſon to them, but himſelfe became his inſtructor: which I attribute to no other conſideration, then that he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:178005:14"/> choſe, to frame him to a wel compoſed <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> then to be excellent in any Art or Profeſſion: <hi>vt modeſtior, non vt lepidior fiat,</hi> a perfection fitter for a mechanicke earner, then a true owner of himſelfe: ſince it is the forming of the minde, not the tongue or hand, that can preferre vs to true felicity.</p>
            <p>Now that we may touch as it were with our finger how much <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> conferres, towards a perfit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; what is more proper and peculiar to the forming and framing of the mind to wiſedome and goodneſſe, then firſt to keepe out vice, and then ſo to worke, prepare, and temper the mind, as it ſhall be alwaies fit to receiue &amp; containe the wholeſome documents of vertue and honeſtie? Which doth <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> ſo naturally and effectually, as all other things, that offer themſelues for this vſe, are in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, left-handed, and ſtepmothers to educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, as one ſayth pretily in his imagined wife, that he would haue her, of a denying behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; as if a fort acceſſiuely ſcituated, could not bee impregnable, ſince aſſaultable: and as he ſaith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he comes too neere, that comes to bee denyed, and as <hi>Ouid,</hi> that great trader into thoſe parts, could neuer find armor of proofe for Chaſtity, but not to be prooued, <hi>caſta eſt quam nemo rogauit,</hi> ſhe's chaſte, whom no tongue yet did taſte: ſo doubtleſſe, he ſhall paſſe the narrow way of Vertue, with fewer impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that his owner of this ſober preuentiue beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, then thoſe alluring countenances, which keep open houſe for all commers: one Phyloſopher would haue bolſters made, to ſtop the eares of yong men, from contagious noyſome ſounds; but he that
<pb facs="tcp:178005:15"/> hath made <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> his Porter, ſhall not need them, ſince his very preſence deters and checks their looſe imaginations, and they dare not confeſſe themſelues to him, that hath their condemnation written in his face: <hi>hoc ſecum certe tuliſset, neminem coram Catonem peccare.</hi> Pedlers open their wares willingeſt to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children: in a word, as they ſay the Amatiſt preuents drunkenneſſe, ſo is <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue againſt the entrance of a number of vices.</p>
            <p>Will wee then frame a man fit to command and obey? to gouerne others and direct himſelfe? a man ſo ſquared by the vnfaileable rules of wiſedome and iudgement, as to know how to become all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to vſe all fortunes? Bind his tender youth to a diſpoſition tempered with <hi>Sadneſſe:</hi> for this man can neither ſeduce his minority with ill examples, nor marre his waxen age, with a falſe impreſſion, too common a condition of theſe diſſolute times: where our children with their milke, and their very firſt words, ſucke in obſcene ſpeeches, and diſſolute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour: and imitation, and cuſtome, hath giuen them the very habite of vice, before they haue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loued, or choſen them.</p>
            <p>But this falls not out to the pupils that are gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by men of this carriage: for ſince it is reſolued, that this <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> is not an accident of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, but a gard hammered out of their diſcourſe and the iſſue of a happie matched diſcretion and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: they doe already ſo well know, that all the allurements of vice offer themſelues, but like play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and iugglers, to ſhew you ſport, and to gaine by you: and this word recreation, is but the outſide of times waſtfull and wilfull conſumption: and that not
<pb facs="tcp:178005:15"/> onely the houres ſo ſpent, are vtterly loſt; but which is farre worſe, this continuall excitation of the beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of man, prouokes his luſtes and ſenſualities vnto an vnquenchable dropſie.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe, as complexions are apter to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of bodily diſeaſes, one then the other; ſo behauiours to the contagion of the mind: mirth is made of pleaſure, and with pleaſure all vices are bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; whereas this <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> is the complexion of a mind that knoweth this, and therefore hates and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines Mirth: I know experience is the chiefeſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that age can produce to proue their right to wiſedome; but that which makes their iudgements ſtrong inough, to make their experience of more vſe, then a bare tale, is a decay of their ſenſes, growne too weake to trade for themſelues, and the fitter to be ſet to our reaſon to make vp a true harmony of all the parts, to the good and preſeruation of the whole: the ſame effect hath <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> with young men, that this decay of nature hath with old; for when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting part, or will of man, is ſo rectified with a ſad conſideration of the true valew of all that the ſenſes preſent vnto her; well may they long to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, with their ſeuerall obiects: but when that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire hath no other aduocate but it ſelfe; it ſoone lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth and forſaketh it ſuite: <hi>Eſchines</hi> aduice to an inquirer after the beſt courſe of life, was, to goe to the Church willingly, to the Warres vpon neceſſity, but to Feaſts vpon no tearmes: what was this, but to praiſe the conſeruation of <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> which in theſe aſſemblies, is for the moſt part betraied: and in the heat of Wine, meat, and company, melted, into the cuſtomes of diſſolute mirth? which made the wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:178005:16"/> Romane complaine, that hee neuer came amongſt men, but returned leſſe man, then when hee went out.</p>
            <p>This made the Phyloſopher that fell a ſleepe at a feaſt, hold his tongue with one hand, and with the other, the part <hi>that they ſay women loue beſt,</hi> but not to ſpeake of: as the two taps, at which Mirth and Pleaſure are drawne out.</p>
            <p>But may I not ſeeme to go too much of one hand, when propoſing inſtructions, I incline rather to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions then additions: ſurely if the nature of man were ſo pure &amp; ſimple, as it had no participation nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mixture with contrarieties &amp; repugnances, there were no way but one; and that one direct: but as he is firſt in his maſſe, or corporial ſubſtance, the iſſue or production of the 4 grand Heterogimical bodies, and after by the ſeuerall and moſt differing powers of his reaſon and will, as vnlike in their likeneſſe and natures, as light and darkeneſſe: there being as much to ſhun, as to follow: I hope I ſhall not erre in my way, if the ſcituation of the end propoſed, drawes me ſometimes about, ſince I vndertake to conduct, not the eye, but the vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Neither will my Reader (I hope) hold himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, if <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> alone, and by it ſelfe, onely brings not in all the materialls neceſſary to the compoſing of a perfit man, and the framing a happineſſe to the full extent of our earthly condition: for ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract is not to be drawne, from a knowledge ſo ouer-clowded as mine, let it ſuffice then and it will: (my indifferent Iudge) that it is of ſo much vſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as though with it onely you cannot make this purchaſe, yet without it, if it be not impoſſible,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:16"/> yet at leaſt moſt difficult, and withall, that though the ſoule in her reuoluings and trauels, may meet thoſe ſolid conſiderations, that are moſt like her ſelfe, wherein as in a glaſſe ſhe beholds her own beauties: yet are they tranſitory, and but the flaſhes of her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation: the habituall poſſeſſion of the graces of the mind, being to be fixed vpon no body, that <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> hath not firſt prepared. This made ſo many of the Ancients, and of thoſe moſt memorable, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of the minde: ſome to throw away their wealth, others to refuſe riches, the graces of Princes, and the fauour of the people: others pull out their owne eyes, and ſome to abandon the ſociety of man; and euen he that might trulieſt be intituled, <hi>Deliciae humani generis,</hi> he that had the attribute,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> to fetch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Heauen, and to place her in Cities; to bring her from the paradiſe of the gods, and tranſplant her in the breſts of men: no doubt embraced a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pouerty; nay euen life it ſelfe, which he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered at the eaſieſt rate, he would not yet accept of, as too delicate and nice a thing, for a worthy and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicke ſpirit, to make account of. If now wee enter into the conſideration of the motiue that made theſe men ſhun what all the world ſo earneſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue: what could it be but to keepe theſe wants afoot, continually to admoniſh them, of their condition, and to cut off all wayes, by which mirth or pleaſure might make their approches or come to the aſſault.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> in the exceſſe of abundance, killed <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Fabritius</hi> in his pouerty, refuſed the golden bribes of the <hi>Samnites;</hi> vpon abundance waits mirth and pleaſure, and vpon them all, the leproſies and deformities of our minds.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:17"/>
            <p>There is not ſo incorrigible a creature as man in proſperity, nor ſo modeſt and reformed as they that Fortune hath not rockt but wak't, the conſequence of which being <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Sadneſse:</hi> behold them in their operations, and wee muſt reiect the one, as a moſt dangerous poyſon, and imbrace the other, for the moſt precious preſeruatiue.</p>
            <p>If yet I haue not proued <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> inſtruction it ſelfe: yet I hope ſhe doth not look with ſo diſfigured a countenance, as when Opinion paints her: and though I cannot ſay, ſhe is the end of knowledge, yet I may well maintaine her the beginning: ſince it is <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> onely that prepares the vnderſtanding, and makes euery man, <hi>Idoneus</hi> auditor, fit to philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phize, and to be diſciples in the ſchoole of Vertue.</p>
            <p>If now it be determined and truely, that the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and beauties of the ſoule, ought to haue the place and honour, aboue thoſe of the body: and the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, beauty and louely proportion of the body, to be preferred before the effeminate deckings, that the body doth rather carry then enioy: ſince it often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that a foule and deformed carkaſe hath a faire and rich wardrop: and if all theſe in their originall eſtimations, were firſt valued, not for their owne ſakes, but as the Ambaſſadours of thoſe inward qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and excellencies, that ſuch complections, ſhapes, and proportions, inſeparably fore-ſhew: <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> I doubt not, both for her outward loueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and inward vertue and vſe, will be allowed for an adornement,<note place="margin">Sadneſſe <hi>ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</hi>
               </note> that doth not alone pleaſe the eye, but the more iudiciall and intellectuall parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, though I am not ignorant, theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry companions are the moſt acceptable to the moſt:
<pb facs="tcp:178005:17"/> yet not alwayes to the beſt, and if they be at times welcome to the vnderſtanding ſort,<note place="margin">Mirth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the beſt.</note> they are receiued to their tables, not counſells: and vſed rather for ſauce for their meate, then ſeaſoning for their iudgements: and are, as was ſayd of <hi>Athens,</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that though many deſired to bee entertayned in, yet few to inhabite: from whence commeth this, but that as they are adorers of mirth, they are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of all ſadde and ſerious conſiderations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to keepe life in laughter, the whole ſtream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their wits is ſpent, vpon the motion of their tongues: In a word, they ſacrifice their earneſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt, their friends to their humour, and to preſent ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all the duties of humanity, honeſty, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: and if ſo; where ſhall we lay hold of them, or to what vſe would they ſerue, but to ſuch a one, as all honeſt natures cannot but ſcorne and diſdaine? vvhereas the ſadde and ſober behauiour makes it one way to allowances, and if it gets not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances ſo faſt, it winnes friends faſter; and though perhaps it bee not alwayes ſo readily entertained, yet it is euermore reſpected: and reaſon, ſince the one with his inceſſant motion weares out it ſelfe, loades the eare, and loathes the eye; whereas the other, in his reſeruedneſſe, maintaines his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in his vnited vigor: and not troubling his braine with his tongue, falls not into the diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of many words: but ſtill holding more in his breſt then vpon his ſhoulders, is ſtrong enough for any aſſault, and prepared to make the beſt vſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and conference. Surely, if behauiour be of ſuch eſtimation, as beauty without it is deformed; and deformity with it is louely, and agreeable to al eyes:
<pb facs="tcp:178005:18"/> if behauiour be the ſoule of the forme, <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> is the ſoule of the ſoule: for ſuch a compoſed ſettled ſmoothneſſe, as diſtaſtes not to day; pleaſeth to morrow, and gets by continuance: no faſhion wins ſo vniuerſally and continually, as that which hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the true tincture of <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> for it ſuppreſſeth the inconſtancy, and buſie turbulency of the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affections: it receiues nothing vpon truſt, or at the firſt ſight; and therefore is alwaies one: neither being troubled with the flouds and ebbes of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: the vanity of the world, the ill imployed pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of greatneſſe, nor the fluctuary motions of the humerous multitude; or at leaſt, if he be ſenſible of their irregularities and confuſions, yet his thoughts are not written in his face: his countenance is not ſignificant: whereas the face and diſpoſition of mirth euer reſembles his laſt thoughts; and vpon euery touch, or taſte of that which is diſpleaſant, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes not the ſtreame of his appetite, it deformes it ſelfe, and like the Moone, is in as many changes, as his fortune: now if the wrangling of children bee troubleſome, the waywardneſſe of men muſt, to a ſtranger, be ridiculous; and to the acquaintance odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and conſequently <hi>Sadneſse</hi> a goodly ornament, that neither diſpleaſeth others, deformes it ſelfe, nor at any time paſſeth the bounds of iudgement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; and though he muſt, as he is man, haue many thoughts to repent, yet few actions. <hi>Primum argumentum compoſitae mentis existimo, poſſe conſiſtere &amp; ſecum morari,</hi> as it is commonly taken for a ſigne of a ſtrong eſtate, and a ſettled diſpoſition, to keepe a certaine houſe, and to loue home: and that ſuch men are the beſt, both comforters and counſellers,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:18"/> of their meane and needy neighbours: ſo is it, with thoſe minds that retire into their owne meditations, and ſcatter not themſelues vpon the irreſolute and inconſtant inuitations of opinion; being moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in their examples; and moſt ſound, in their counſels; outwardly goodly markes of direction, for them that are ignorant in their courſe: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, moſt happy and ſafe harbours and hauens for them, that either by weather, or weakneſſe, or any other, either ſuſpicion or knowledge of impediment, dare not put out into the vaſte and profound muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities and dangers of this Ocean of the World: if now a mole on the cheek be an ornament to beauty; <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> is the ſame to wit; and if wit, like quickſiluer, bee too nimble for it owne conſeruation, <hi>Sadneſse</hi> doth more then containe it: for it refines, and fixes it: Iewels and rich apparell adorne the Poſſeſſor, and exact from ſtrange eyes a reuerence and reſpect: <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> the graue and euer becomming robe of iudgement, repreſents to all vnderſtandings the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable account of all ſo adorned: if the all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing apparell of women, that meaſured by their modeſty, leaues nothing for the incurſions, of gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wanton eyes to make ſpoyle of, and doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proclaime their ſoules fairer then their bodies, but their bodies fairer then they are: with leauing the face, eye and hand, as a broken ſentence to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by imagination: <hi>Sadneſse</hi> doth the ſame; for the interiour parts doubling and redoubling the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the mind, in ſuch ſort, that euen fooles that Nature hath euen hidden vnder this behauiour, haue often eſcaped cenſure; and vnder title of a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fellow hath hidden a moſt empty and ſenſeleſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:178005:19"/> for who can tell the contents of a claſped booke, or inuentory, or a lockt Wardrop? Now as it conceales the foole, it illuſtrates the wiſe man. For as the Sun breaking through a cloude, lets fall the golden treſſes of his beames vpon the gloomy ayery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, after his abſence, with a much more reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent maieſtie, then when continually vnmasked, he proſtitutes his beauties vnto euery eye, and makes not onely the Shepheard, but his flocke weary of his company, and ſeeke ſhade and ſhelter to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from his too faſt fixed ſight: euen ſo the well wayed motions of the ſad behauiour commands at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and the ſtayednes of his carriage prepares a conſent before hearing, as due to him that lets no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing paſſe without due conſideration.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if one of the greateſt Philoſophers determined ſilence, a more excellent quality then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence: I haue the ayd of his authority, ſince <hi>Sadneſse</hi> is the ſeate of ſilence, where ſhee onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in ſafety, and where without all noyſe, trouble or tumult, ſhe enioyes the intelligence and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations of the ſoule: which the children of mirth cannot heare; for their owne noyſe: nor taſte, their mouthes are ſo furd with bodily pleaſures.</p>
            <p>And now I will appeale to the eye, if theſe lignia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and features of <hi>Sadneſse,</hi> be not more goodly and becomming then thoſe of mirth: ſurely if they be not more delightfull, they are more contenting: the difference of which, I refer to the Iudiciall, and to thoſe that valew things by their neereneſſe, and reſemblance of thoſe of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for gouernment, though the world be not made of Attomes, yet the body of mans reputation,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:19"/> is the concurrence of his ſpeeches, actions and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: which ought to aduiſe all men, not to neglect the leaſt motion, either of mind or body: leſt it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens a deformity vpon all: ſhall we expect this from mirth? it were in vaine, and to preſcribe it, were loſt labour; it is compoſed wholly of contrarieties: for take a quantity of idle breath, ſublimated into a ieſt, a proportion of laughter, ſome mimicke trickes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the face or the body, and boyle them ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly in wine, that you cannot know one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you haue the moſt receiued receit of mirth: but who will vndertake to giue aſſurance, that this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired crue, ſhall not violate the dignity of men: and ſo gouerne themſelues, that ſhame and deriſion ſhall not haue more right to them, then they to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vliſses</hi> dranke of <hi>Circes</hi> cuppe, and was not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: the morall is, a wiſe man may waſh his mouth, but not quench his thirſt, with pleaſure: for, he that aymes onely at mirth and pleaſure, hits ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and repentance; as well becauſe it makes him raſh and inconſiderate in his courſes, when to buy mirth, he ſells all the reſpects and duties that hee owes to ineſtimable vertue, and his owne preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as that it being to the mind, as a ſtoaue to the body, that ſo opens the pores, as the leaſt ayre giues a blow to the health, ſo the leaſt aduerſity or frowne of fortune, deiects their minds, and layes them open, either to a rauening fury, or a baſe bewayling: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that will not ſeale the worſt of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> let him beware of deuoting himſelfe to mirth, for they only feele the water intolerable cold, that goe into it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary hot. The Philoſophers that impoſed ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb facs="tcp:178005:20"/> vpon their Schollers for their firſt inſtruction, could intend nothing elſe, but the ſettling and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the mind: from whence ariſeth that habite of <hi>Sadneſſe,</hi> that gaue them power of themſelues; and withall of all things that came within the bounds of their knowledge: if not to gaine by, yet not to loſe.</p>
            <p>To what end ſhould I produce the witneſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous ancients, from whome ſcarce a ſmile was euer drawne, and yet were ſuch, as neuer loſt oppur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; that preſented it ſelfe, to do others good, or themſelues right: nor euer loſt that power, force, and tranquillity of their owne minds, in any of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes tranſmutations, that is wont ſo to ouercome the reaſon of men, as like tranſformed creatures, there can bee nothing more different then them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? Neither will I authorize my opinion, by the example of our bleſſed Sauiour, who was neuer ſeene to laugh: nor <hi>Salomons</hi> ſacred counſell, that it was better to go to the houſe of mourning, then mirth, leſt the worldly man, that makes prouiſion only for the building of his Babel, caſt me off as an vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and impertinent counſellor: though it ſhal then (gentle Reader) inſenſibly, and without thy trouble prepare thee for the beſt worke of thy life, which is the life eternall: yet whileſt thou wilt be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to thy temporall imployments, it is alſo of moſt effectuall importance.</p>
            <p>Deſireſt thou to be reputed wiſe? It is her viſibleſt forme; not to bee importuned with vaine and idle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany? they feare <hi>Sadnes</hi> too much to follow thee.</p>
            <p>To bee the ſafe Cabinet of thy owne and thy friends ſecrets? <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> is the parent of ſilence, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of ſecrecy.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:20"/>
            <p>To be temperate? where <hi>Sadneſse</hi> is Porter, few vaine deſires are admitted.</p>
            <p>Not to bee precipitate in thy actions? Where <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> keepes the liſts of conſideration, alwaies cleere and free, from the intruſions of paſſion, the ſoule cannot but gouerne all things by the regular and iudiciall power of reaſon, as ſhee that knowes time call to conſultations, ſhuts out repentance.</p>
            <p>In a word, if there be any way to be troad in by our feete of clay, we are out of the reach of Fortune, out of the power of our paſſions, and in the full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of our ſelues, wee may liue in a continuall calme: where from the height of a cleere &amp; impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable iudgement, wee may ſafely and inſenſibly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the world, by this time ſo farre vnder vs, as all ſuch vaine deſires, as had wont to make vs ſuiters and followers to her, haue loſt ſight of their inamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red obiects, it is by the way of <hi>Sadneſſe:</hi> who doth not alone inrich vs by that it brings, but preſerues vs ſo by keeping out all inordinate appetites, diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered affections, and thoſe humors of bloud and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, who where they are fauoured, do vſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and expell, not onely all honeſt and vertuous actions, but euen the very thoughts that doe but ſeeme to be well affected.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I (good Reader) preſented to thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance the ſweeteſt, and beſt conditioned com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of the life of man, which if you will but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue vpon tryall, I deſire no more: be not ſeduced by opinion, and thou maiſt bee as happie as this world can make thee: for though the outward pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er makes men great, yet is the inward, that makes men vertuous, and vertue onely that produceth a
<pb facs="tcp:178005:21"/> happineſſe, that can indure the teſt of all times and changes.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt I omit to anſwere them that would hide their baſe choice in the confuſion of words, and ſo will haue their mirth to be ioy; but he is worſe then blind that knowes them not a ſunder, mirth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather an apiſh vnquietneſſe, then a ſolide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment: beſides, it liues not of it ſelfe, it depends vpon fortune, vpon time, health, and many outward accidents; and liues but vpon borrowing, whereas ioy being as the ſhadow of vertue, or the effect of the inward and inſeparable cauſe of a good life, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer from home, neuer in a cloude, neuer ſubiect to alteration, alwayes one, and therefore not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies happie, but therefore happineſſe it ſelfe: and yet to make the difference more apparant, behold their pictures drawne by two excellent Maſters, <hi>res ſeuera eſt verum gaudium,</hi> which if <hi>Sadneſse</hi> reſembles not more liuely then mirth, let your iudgement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, and now for mirth, I am ſure this was made, it is ſo like her, <hi>riſu inepto, res ineptior nulla eſt;</hi> if you define mirth without laughing, you ſpeake of ſomewhat els, and leaue your errand behind you, but it hath been ſo often determined, that they are ſo farre from all one, as they are not ſo much as alike: as further to labour in ſo manifeſt a truth, will rather obſcure, then inlighten it.</p>
            <p>I will then include this queſtion in this definitiue ſentence, <hi>falſo de laetitia opinantur ſiquidem ab vtriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gaudio ſcilicet &amp; natura, diuerſa eſt,</hi> it hath not onely loſt the challenge to ioy, but to nature; hee then that drew man within the compaſſe of <hi>animal riſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> was rather a confeſſor to good companions,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:21"/> then a wiſe ſuruey or of the little world of man.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, if thou haſt but Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly enough to ſuſpend thy opinion, whatſoeuer thou art, thou haſt me in the power of thy cenſure: I doubt not but you ſhall bee beholding to your iudgement, to free mee from the hereſie of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſome other thinke, that I haue reſtrained the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of man, in commending <hi>Sadneſse</hi> vnto him: let him know, I haue not determined it the end, but the way onely; an entry or paſſage, that of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, hath a world much more ſpacious and pleaſant, then that of this ſide, comprehended by mirth: which is little, poore and tranſitory: if yet there be ſome that will bring this euidence for their libertie, <hi>Laetitia tuuenem, fraus decet triſtis ſenem,</hi> it is but like a licence to eate fleſh in Lent, for them that are weake and ſickly; or like a lawe that prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all perſons to weare gay clothes, and Iewels, but players and curtiſans: which was then taken for a marke of ſcorne, not for a priuiledge of grace and aduantage: which if they ſhall pleaſe to take ſo too, they ſhall haue the leſſe to anſwere for, and I ſhall neither haue loſt my labour, nor their fauour: if not, I muſt yet challenge the allowance of the wiſeſt, which are the oldeſt, who if they ſhould yeeld to an extreme, would rather ratifie that Philoſopher that euer wept, then this that tooke no more pittie of himſelfe, and of the madnes of mankind, then to ſpend his life in laughter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178005:22"/>
            <head>THE PRAYSE OF the Emperour <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>APOSTATA: His Princely vertues, and finall Apoſtacie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Dare not affirme him temperate, that ſhuns ſurfets; nor him graue, that deſpiſeth lightneſſe; nor him valiant, that loues to conuerſe with danger: It is no precious thing, my opinion, and yet I am afraid to ſpend it: let Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, a Gods name, be thought trim fellowes for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of the liues of men, as if they had come yeſterday from the Fates; for my part, except I may haue leaue to paſſe through the inſide of them, I can ſay nothing: for all theſe are no more a kin to Vertue, then baſeneſſe may challenge of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, becauſe their names ſound alike: it being not Temperance, not grauity, not Fortitude; except the
<pb facs="tcp:178005:23"/> cauſe that moues theſe effects, bee vertues. The World affoords not a more apt example then this Emperour, the Hiſtorie of whoſe life is full of ſo many excellent things, as hardly he that is a votary againſt the world, and hath nothing to thinke of, but keeping his vow, may equall him in all theſe outward apparances, that fauourable iudgements call the way to heauen; but in the depth of impiety; againe, not the moſt reprobate,<note place="margin">His tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> comparable: yet was he ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, as he neuer ſurfeted nor vometed oftner, then he was made <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and that of cheeſe: in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations of the fleſh none chaſter,<note place="margin">His chaſtity &amp; thrift.</note> no vnthrift of his treaſure, and time, in publike ſports, a common diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of greatneſſe:<note place="margin">Not giuen to pleaſure.</note> no laſciuious pleaſure did ruſt and conſume his time, ſo couetous was he of it, as the very nights he deuided into vpholding his body, the bettering his minde, the ſeruing his country; he needed not <hi>Alexanders</hi> ball of mettall to awake him, for the thinneſſe of his dyet required not much ſleep,<note place="margin">His moderate dyet.</note> whereas the other was a good fellow, and gaue his hot conſtitution leaue to leade him to banquets and quaffings.<note place="margin">His valour.</note> For his valour, aske all the Hiſtories of his time, and you ſhall finde they make ſo great a noyſe about no body: but all theſe helpe him not, ſo irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious a hart poſſeſt them, proceeding moſt of them out of his education, ſome from his nature, none from vertue: how iuſtly then may we ſuſpect our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of men that carry the forme of the exacteſt liues? Me thinkes it were well, if they were let alone vntill the next world: for it is to be doubted, whether praiſes be not like raine that increaſeth weeds, as well as nouriſheth the corne: for it begets Hypocrites, and for the truely vertuous, they neither care for it,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:23"/> nor neede it: if all men were of my mind, they that are good, and they that neuer came neerer then a deſire to be thought ſo; ſhould ſhortly be diſcerned one from another: for his ſoft pacing, his graue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and conſtant countenance, ſhall not worke a whit vpon me, no, not a ſpeech well read, with the head and the fingers finely placed; no, not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vice in choller, and putting off his Hatt when vertue is called; no, not the defying the World, nor challenging the combate of concupiſcence: theſe are but words of courſe, but promiſes, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: <hi>Promittas facito, quid enim promittere laedit? pollicitis diues, quilibetieſſe potest:</hi> But this it is to write without the hope of gaining by a <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> or the am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bition of method; my matter, my ſtile, hang diſioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and vnſemented, neither of them keepes their place, but gallops, and trots and ambles; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I neuer gaue <hi>Tully</hi> an houre for any of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorike: I ſend not my words awooing, I care not, ſo they can get to their iournies end, though they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caper, nor dance: there is a grace in the ſound of words, but it is not mine, I giue my thoughts clothes ſodainly, and ſo fit, that they may be vnderſtood; but whether they be in faſhion and wel ſhaped, is not my care: I am of too rude a nature to be ſo nice, and mine eares are ſo harſh, that I could neuer yet vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſweetnes of the ſound of opinion; but to that I take in hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, let me not be condemned for my Subiect: he was an ill man, that was his loſſe, but this ill was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ill at the iourneyes end; for moſt of his actions were good here, and had been good for euer, if they had not ſerued an ill maſter: but at the worſt, Vertue
<pb facs="tcp:178005:24"/> is not ſo proud as not to extract what may bee made good, out of ill for there is a ſpirit in vice, that being cunningly drawne out, will ſerue euen the beſt: ſo ful it is of a quick and peircing vigour: he hath a poore Library to behold, that reades onely the good; let him turne ouer all, that deſires to bee profound; let him earne Vertue with digging it out of vice, and he will keepe it the better: let him fetch it out of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trals of ill, that will glory of his conqueſt; from thoſe ſoft miniſters of the mind, the Arts which make the ſoule read to the body, and make practice but a ſlight, through the minds foreknowledge.</p>
            <p>This Prince came to the managing Armes, not with ſuch a people whoſe weakeneſſe was fit to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a nouice, but with thoſe fierce and warlike; yet was he victorious, and made thoſe that were wont to be feared, feare: <hi>Qui alijs terrore eſſe conſueuerat, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſibi timere coegit:</hi> who allowes not of ſuch an excellent beginning? When I heare of any great Souldier, I aske his age, when if old, it takes away mine admiration; for vpon a wiſe minority I looke with greateſt affection: But here comes a priuy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to know intents by, <hi>Sed haec laus etiam miſerrima ambitionis labe contaminata est, cum ſe Auguſtum ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari voluit:</hi> ſo greedy are thoſe minds that intend onely to ſerue their owne turne; no ſooner haue they attained to an atchieuement commendable, but they enforce prayſes out of the mouthes of men; they will ſwagger for titles and reſpect; yea, it becomes Lord, euen of themſelues; for reaſon of more waight, that in another mans caſe ſhould haue preuailed, with the eyes of ambition ſeemes dwarfiſh, weake, and little. That wiſe and warlike ſeruant to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:178005:24"/> of Spaine,<note n="*" place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Alua.</hi>
               </note> the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> hath much of his glory dusked, by an Hiſtorian, that relates the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Don Antonio Prior of <hi>Crato,</hi> commonly called the King of Por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tugall.</note> Prior of <hi>Crato</hi> would haue come to a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: but hee would not heare of it, becauſe it could not haue bin then ſaid, he conquered Portugal with the ſword: of ſuch a valew were a few idle words, as his maſters profit and his own truth were thought things meete to giue place to this wind, to this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: But behold how Fortune ſometimes playes the ſame part that wiſedome doth, and brings a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull end to falſe beginnings: <hi>Vnde bellum ciuile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociſsimum eſſet conſecutum, niſi mors pene repentina conſtantium ante ſuſtuliſset:</hi> thus doth that blinde guide make arguments to ouerthrow iudgement: thus vpon the death of <hi>Alexander de medicis, Coſimo</hi> was inthroned, being ſcarce out of the downe of his childhood, without much paine or ſtudy, that had coſt his predeceſſors much trouble, much care: ſo doth it pleaſe the diuine wiſedome, to demonſtrate to mortall eyes their impotency; for it is hee, there is no fortune, it is hee that makes thoſe things that ſeeme to haue idle beginnings, proue profitable at the end. Both theſe examples, though in ſome things different, yet agree in the demonſtrating: thoſe things that wee vnderſtand not, and therefore call chances, haue often as faire an end as things propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; which is the will of heauen to teach vs earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that our purpoſes cannot go whither they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, without his pleaſure. At his Coronation,<note place="margin">His Coronation.</note> &amp; after, he ſeemed modeſtly to miſlike his greatnes, the common tricke of ambition, who ſtill deſires to ſeeme careleſſe of what he chiefely thirſts after; if it be not ſo, it is as with vs all, that like thoſe things
<pb facs="tcp:178005:25"/> that are fartheſt off: hee vſed often to proteſt, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſe amplius aſſecutum, quam vt occupatior interiret:</hi> a ſpeech that, me thinkes, drawes the nature of his place liuely, and withall, the happineſſe of his place; for there cannot be a more noble ſtate, then that which perforce bids vs to bee induſtrious and buſie; a more worthy buſineſſe can there not bee, then the imployment of a Prince: hee feeles not death that dyeth thus, he hath other buſineſſe, then to breed thoughts of terror; and for them that find greatneſſe, and yet make death terrible, it comes from the abuſe of their authority: for they truly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, are vnſenſible of ſmart, and feare not death, nor his worſt countenance.</p>
            <p>After his poſſeſſion of the Empire, hee inuaded <hi>Perſia,</hi> drawne the more willingly, by a perſwaſion, that his body had gotten <hi>Alexander</hi> his ſoule, and ſhould haue his ſucceſſe. Good Lord, into what vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and ridiculous imaginations are they led, that haue not the anchor-hold of Religion! Went it no further, then this, it were moſt precious, for it keepes our thoughts in good order, which otherwiſe would make vs all as wilde as mad-men: for we bred Monſters and miſ-ſhapen things in our braine, which did not the conſcience reduce into faſhion (which conſcience is the childe of Diuinity) wee ſhould not touch one another for feare of breaking: but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſuch a perſwaſion carrieth higher and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer then euer meant, inforcing imitation. I knew once a fellow, meane enough, and as meanly qualited, being ſayd to be like a great man, began to ingender ſtirring thoughts, of ſpirit, of well doing, and, at the laſt, arriued at the pitch of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="tcp:178005:25"/> worthy fellow; but within a while this muſt be caſt off. It is not amiſſe at the firſt to giue children plummes for learning their leſſon, but afterwards they muſt loue learning for knowledges ſake, theſe for vertues. Of the happineſſe of his perfections, and then of his imperfections: his temperance<note place="margin">His temperance.</note> carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it a number of commodities; for beſides health, it maintained the ſtrength and viuacitie of his ſpirit, which the aboundance of eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is wont to quench; at leaſt kill: his ſleeps were thereby leſſe (the drowner of the ſpirits) being the image of death, the maker of the vnderſtanding dull,<note place="margin">His moderate ſleepe.</note> and ſenſeleſſe: but the beſt quality is the cooling of luſt, which banqueting and exceſſe is wont to kindle in the body, and the body to fire the minde; but this abſtinence brings the other vnder, and curbes luſt, which vſually melteth away, and ſo becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the maintainer of the life of man. His ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is not of the leaſt conſequence, the life of the Prince being the book of the ſubiect,<note place="margin">The Princes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects booke.</note> from which nothing may withdraw them: though his abundance may ſeeme to licenſe him, and exempt them, they will take it for no anſwere,<note place="margin">Prouidence of time and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> nor in trueth is it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, for I thinke they were lent him to doe others good with, not himſelfe hurt: prouident in ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his treaſure, parcimonious of his time, both ſtrengtheners of himſelfe, for by the firſt, hee comes not to neede others, by the laſt not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of time, for they liue the ſhorteſt (though moſt yeeres) that miſpend it: a lamentable thing, euen worſe then mortality, for this death is worſe then that: a great meanes of this, was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of delighting the people,<note place="margin">His delighting the people.</note> and of honouring
<pb facs="tcp:178005:26"/> their gods with ſundry publike ſports; and what might be the reaſon beſides ignorance, in the <hi>Roman</hi> State vpholding theſe, I can but gheſſe; it might be with their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minalty, as with our little children, who if not feede with ſports will growe wayward and crie, ſo tickliſh are popular States, where it is but a ſtep from the beſt to the worſt, that if they bee not kept buſie, they will mutiny and growe into miſlikes; to doe well they muſt be appointed their very thoughts, with feeding them with light ſtuffe, farre from the matter. Wherefore, if in no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,<note place="margin">Monarchike gouernment beſt.</note> the Monarchy is to be honoured as the Prince of gouernment, and eſpecially thoſe of ſucceſſion, where the ambitious and rebellious nature hath not ſo much to worke vpon, the people being euer moſt affectionate to the bloud Royall, and God hauing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly prohibited the vſing violence to his Anointed: the ſecret meaning of theſe ſports was beſt knowne to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> but of the diſeaſes of them I haue noted.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Diſeaſes in the Romane ſports. The firſt diſeaſe.</note> 2. In the time of <hi>Nero,</hi> and both of them me thinkes likely to follow: The one of them was, when the Procurators, Proconſulls, or other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, had abuſed the authority of their places, with pilling and taxing the ſubiects of the Empire, they came to <hi>Rome</hi> and made their peace, with giuing the people the ſight of ſword-plaiers, or ſom ſuch things. Here is the Prohibition: <hi>Edixit</hi> Caeſar <hi>ne quis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus, aut Procurator, qui Prouinciam obtinert ſpectaculum gladietorum, aut ferarum, aut quod aliud lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicrum aederet;</hi> this is the medicine, the diſeaſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: <hi>Nam ante non minus tali largitione, quam cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripiendis pecunijs ſubiectos affligebant, dum quae libidine deliquerant, ambitu propugnant:</hi> It is a circumſpection
<pb facs="tcp:178005:26"/> moſt behouefull for the Magiſtrate, to take away the meanes of getting theſe keyes to open the peoples heart with, which is to be certainlieſt performed, with ſtopping all ſprings, that would feed them, but the fountaine of chiefe authority; for otherwiſe, they will like tame birds, readily come to the call of him that giues them meate. The other was,<note place="margin">The ſecond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</note> how apt the celebrations were to nouriſh a laſciuious Prince, ſhewing &amp; directing the way to ſoftneſſe, &amp; exceſſe: which is well approued by this Empire of liberty and feſtiualls, and the ancient Laconian ſtrictneſſe, where there was neuer riotous Prince; in the other, euery ſecond or third Emperour a Monſter:<note place="margin">Power in a wanton hand ruinates his charge.</note> there is not a more dangerous thing then power in a wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand, which euery way ruinates his charge; for if it liue to growe olde, it becomes tyranny, in the meane time corrupts himſelf and Common-wealth: the naturall man louing bodily pleaſures, when cheriſhed by the life of a laſciuious Prince, the nature of it is doubled. <hi>Eſt vulgus cupiens voluptatum, &amp; ſi eo Princeps trahat laetum:</hi> They are well contented with ſuch a Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, alas, their countenances are vnfit guides for a Stateſ-man; me thinks they are like the ſence of taſt, that neuer conſidereth the operation, but taſte: faire otherwiſe was this Prince, which he layes to his edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, though I think Nature had made him of too rough a mould to bee carried with ſuch lightneſſe; yet might it be his familiarity with letters, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the mind ſo high, as moſt other things appeare baſe and contemptible; this ſpeech is the childe of ſuch a minde, <hi>turpe eſſe ſapienti, cum habeat animam, captare laudes ex corpore:</hi> it is a ſpeech worthie of the worthieſt mouth, and proclaimes to the ambitious
<pb facs="tcp:178005:27"/> where to buy the beſt glory and commendations. It reſteth to tell what were the waights that made his vices<note place="margin">His vices.</note> heauieſt, the lightneſſe of his nature, or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, his purſuite of vnlawfull knowledges, and laſtly, his ambition and cueoting dominion. I doe not cry fie of inconſtancy,<note place="margin">Firſt his incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, &amp;c.</note> or curſe it, for by the leaue of ages ſettledneſſe, there is neuer a Peſant in the world traines vp youth better, I abhorre it in age, and ſtop my noſe at it; but youths beſt lectures are read by inconſtancy;<note place="margin">Prayſe of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in youth.</note> neuer ſtampe, miſtris experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, at my opinion, for were it not lawfull for age to forget, I ſhould call you ingratefull, for Inconſtancy was your nurſe, and all the ſtrange experiments you haue paſſed, ſhe carried you through. But when age begins to decline a body, it is time to leaue it: hee hath ſpent his time ill, that knowes not then what to truſt to, which knowne muſt be held to the death, yea and in death.<note place="margin">Martyrdome one of the beſt deaths.</note> Martyrdome is one of the beſt faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned cuts that Dame <hi>Atropos</hi> hath: me thinks, at that time Death playeth a gallant conductor, and leads vs to an aſſault that paſſed, deſerues tryumph, his ill directed knowledges deſerue the greateſt blame, for all knowledges whatſoeuer that haue poyſoned man,<note place="margin">His ill deriued knowledge.</note> with the perſwaſion of ſtanding onely vpon his own ſtrength, are both feeble and impious; they are like legges that haue onely ſtrength to carry the body, where it may deſtroy it ſelfe: amongſt theſe Magick and Aſtrologie,<note place="margin">Magicke and Aſtrologie.</note> the ſtudies of vaine melancholicke natures,<note place="margin">Diuell-binders.</note> but eſpecially the diuel-binders are the moſt ſottiſh people in the world: for what can bee more ridiculous then to thinke hearbs, ſpels, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, can enforce infernall ſpirits to be ruled by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men, or that God will giue a power to his Name
<pb facs="tcp:178005:27"/> abuſed? But Aſtrologie is not ſo ill. The other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, is the game that the diuell playes at faſt and looſe with man, but the abuſe of knowledge, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the fineſt metals, deſerues more pitty; of all the great troupes that goe this way, I find few ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued at an indifferent commendation; I cannot tel, they are cut off either by pride, vanity, or contempt; this is the couſenage of partiality; doe you thinke there is ſuch an excellency in hauing ſlubbered an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle?</hi> Fie, no. If you vnderſtood <hi>Aristotle,</hi> you might be bettered; there is not ſuch a vertue in <hi>genus</hi> and <hi>ſpecies,</hi> as you haue ſet it downe in your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentory, they are but names; and Art it ſelfe but the ſtilts of a cripple: for if we could go without them, what ſhould we do with them? Vanity, prides mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, belongeth to this crue: ſuch are thoſe that hauing taken a doſſe of <hi>Cicero,</hi> preſently learne their tongues to dance a Cinque-pace; theſe vtter Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo like <hi>Ciceroes</hi> as they ſeeme the ſame, ſo well can they enforce a circumſtance and neatly ſlide from one limme of Rethoricke to another: away with this whoriſh eloquence, with this breath-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, it becomes not the grauity of a profeſſed ſcholler, no more then it doth a Generall, reckoned to be skilfull at his needle. The laſt is Pride in graine,<note place="margin">His contempt of others.</note> contempt; an humor ſodden in ſelfe opinion, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe killing the loue of his countrey, &amp; countrymen, the perſwaſion to make him to apply the riches of his mind to the benefit of others, but this is taken away; for contempt and loue were neuer friends, and then he is no other then a buried Treaſure:<note place="margin">To know what contempt is.</note> This diſeaſe is to bee knowne by ſeparating his cuſtomes from the world, by an eye ful of diſdain, by a countenance
<pb facs="tcp:178005:28"/> borrowed from the picture of ſome old Philoſopher: for no people am I more ſorry, then for theſe, which abuſe the picture of our firſt and moſt bleſſed ſtate: they that deſire cure, let them goe to <hi>Seneca, Frons noſtra, populo conueniat,</hi> and after more thorowly, <hi>Id agamus, vt meliorem vitam ſequamur quam vulgus, non vt contrariam:</hi> I am glad yet that <hi>Seneca's</hi> time was troubled with theſe inke-horne Bragards, as well as wee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His ambition.</note>But this Emperours coueting dominion, of which I ſhall ſpeake like one in a dreame, for I cannot think like a Prince, and I am glad of it, for they are thoughts too bigge for me, but as I gheſſe, Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is more naturall and profitable, in a Prince then priuate men: for the definition of <hi>vtile &amp; honeſtum</hi> with them, and vs, is not all one, our ſtates and our profeſſions differ, and all one inſtrument will not ſerue vs.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IVLIANS</hi> Dialogue of the <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">His Dialogue of the <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
                  </note>I Deſire to haue the picture of famous men by mine eare not mine eye, I preferre the Hiſtorian, before the Painter, I get nothing by the faſhion of his face, but by the knowledge of his life: the pen is the beſt penſell, which drawes the mind, the other, that tells you the ſtature and proportion of the body may delight, not profit; giue me therfore their works; if writers; if not, their liues written by others: thus thinke I of bookes (the iſſue of our minds) all which are not without ſome profit, for there is no ſoule altogether barren, but eſpecially thoſe that are able,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:28"/> and doe write in earneſt, thoſe binde the whole world to them, for they diſſolue their ſpirits, to make theirs more precious, and by the helpe of time haue made that excellent cordiall, that the ſoule diſgeſting may recouer, and bee preſerued againſt our naturall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ignorance. I ſucked not long enough of my Schoole-maſter to proue a Commentor,<note place="margin">The Authors di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</note> I cannot fetch words from their ſwadling bands, nor make them interpret the quality of the things knowne by them, I tract them not, nor ſet a brand of them when I meete them, nor compare the words of one Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor with another: if I can make ioyning worke of the matter, I goe contented, for I worke not for words: and thus nature hath framed me, &amp; I will not goe to ſurgery for an alteration; for me thinkes it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a gentle ſpirit well, to leaue the droſſe and fly to the matter, he writes not vnder the hard reſtraint of feare or gaine, but gallantly giues the World the trauels of his minde, and it is gallantly, for a Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary liberalliſt is in little better ſtate then a <hi>Renegado:</hi> let him then that courts his cenſurers with ſweet titles for feare of bitterneſſe, or him that ſends his booke of a voyage in hope of gaine, tend this cutting vp words and ſuch ſtuffe: but he that writes ſo purely as to want theſe, let him run into things of worth, and fetch ſecrets out of the entrals of actions: I haue read Hiſtory, but they ſeldome doe any more then make the times confeſſe; ſome vpon Hiſtory, moſt ſimple, ſome better, others dangerous; but this Dialogue hath of the vertue of both, and little of their idlenes, full of excellent obſeruation, and withal quick: ſo wel did the ſtomak of mine vnderſtanding like it, that ſhe boyled longer then ordinary, &amp; here is the digeſtion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:29"/>
               <p>It is not my maner to be buſie about the maner of the feaſt, the place, nor other circumſtances, let it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the Author makes <hi>Romulus</hi> inuite his ſucceſſours to a feaſt, at whoſe entrance <hi>Sylenus, Iupiters</hi> buffone hits them where they were left vnarmed by Vertue.</p>
               <p>I promiſe neither method nor antiquitie; but after my faſhion thus:<note place="margin">Iulius Caeſars entrance.</note> Firſt <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> enters, of whom <hi>Sylenus</hi> bids <hi>Iupiter</hi> beware, leſt he plots his depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; for hee is (ſayth hee) great and fayre; thus dangerous is the neighbour-hood of Ambition:<note place="margin">Caeſars ambition.</note> for all other affections that are wont to maintaine ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are not here; for Ambition loues nothing but it ſelfe, nor pitties, nor regards: ſo both commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his reaſon and paſſion to bee ſlaues to this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is good onely for that, to all other dangerous. Beſides the humour, he had two inſtruments belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, he was great and faire; alas, what account ſhould we make of our reaſon? ſince ſhe ſuffereth the vaineſt occaſions to beget the ſeriouſeſt purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Is it not pitifull that Valour ſhould be beholding to the Drumme and Trumpet, and flying of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and the glittering of Armour? Yet is it, and I thinke few ſpirits, but amongſt the reſt haue found theſe the inflamer of courage: no leſſe abſurd is the election of a Magiſtrate by his beautie;<note place="margin">Not good to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate for his beauty.</note> yet is it common for that Whoriſh affection to preuaile, the which rank'd with this greatneſſe ouercomming ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, when men whoſe euidence lyeth in their titles; ſhall poſſeſſe places where wiſedome is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeful, <hi>&amp; patrias laudes ſentiat eſſe ſuas.</hi> Of al which there is to be noted the baſeneſſe of our choyce, the ſluggiſhneſſe of our reaſon, for not forbidding the banes. And laſtly, how they throw themſelues into
<pb facs="tcp:178005:29"/> the hands of Fortune, with managing theſe high things ſo baſely. In the deſcription of <hi>Octauius</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance,<note place="margin">Octauius en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</note> I note <hi>Poetries</hi> power, he makes him appeare in diuers colours, which, me thinks,<note place="margin">His Poetry, and Policie.</note> doth here more handſomely then the plaine truth: for it had not bin ſo fit to haue ſayd, Policy ſutes his forme like the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and alters as it alters: of him, <hi>Sylenus, Papae, quam varium hoc animal,</hi> ſuch muſt be policy, for his trade is with the diuers diſpoſitions of man, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them muſt be diuers.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Tiberius</hi> with a graue &amp; cruel countenance,<note place="margin">Tiberius en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</note> who, he after paints full of ſcarres and ſcabbes, as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of his tyranny and intemperance, to whom <hi>Sylenus, Longe alius mihi nunc, quam ante videres:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His tyranny and intemperance.</note> But, me thinkes, his Verſe is not rightly applyed, for Tyrants are euer deformed, mary, feare in their liues makes it inward, after their deaths apparant; thus pretily doth time mock mortality, firſt tying one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuffering the other to beate them, then the loſed, tyed, and the tyed loſed: thus tyranny and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection: tyranny as long as it laſts buffets his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but death at laſt giues the loſer a time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, when he woundeth their memories, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare or danger.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Silenus</hi> aſſaults his abominable life in the Iland <hi>Caprea,</hi> in no life doe the blemiſhes of life ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſo viſibly as in Princes, whoſe height and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as it may do much, ſo is it moſt obſerued. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hee lets him ſcape for <hi>Seianus,</hi> his doting vpon whom, was much more impardonable then the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Claudius,</hi> becauſe the former profeſſed craft, the other alwaies gouerned by ſmocks and ſlaues.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Claudius</hi> entrance<note place="margin">Claudius en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance.</note> he repeats a Comedy, and
<pb facs="tcp:178005:30"/> after complaines of <hi>Romulus,</hi> for ſuffering him to come without <hi>Naciſſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His committing his affaires to others.</note> 
                  <hi>Palantus,</hi> and his wife <hi>Meſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina:</hi> thus it happens with them that beare the names of great places, and lay their execution vpon others: thus with them that are ſo tender hearted as to bee led by others: thus haue I often obſerued ſeruile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to vndermine their maſters, there being great loſſe in granting to the will of interceſſors, for the gift is theirs, the thanks anothers; wherefore it is the duty of diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſerue to themſelues the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of importance, and he that giueth, to be vnknown himſelfe to him that he giues. Now comes <hi>Nero</hi> and his harpe:<note place="margin">Neroes entrance delighting with playing on the harpe.</note> nothing is ſo faſt tyed to vs as our faults, we are neuer mentioned without them, they hackney our names to death, and neuer leaue ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them till they haue killed them. This man, ſaith <hi>Silenus</hi> imitates <hi>Apollo,</hi> in the meane time behold his miſſhapen courſe, that deſtinated to an Empire, purſues the facultie of a Muſician: I neuer ſee any that profeſſe skill in many things: in theſe hie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters much leſſe; one being inough for one: There followes a troupe together, though <hi>Vindex</hi> ſhewes the ſuppreſſion of tyranny, is behouefull to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,<note place="margin">Galba.</note> but dangerous to the party. <hi>Galba</hi> was euer too little or too big, for his fortune, beeing thought fit for an Empire whileſt priuate, when an Emperour, vnworthy, and ended his ſlaues ſlaue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Otho.</note>
                  <hi>Otho</hi> might haue beene examined about the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Lucitania,</hi> whether hee poſſeſt not that, to be diſpoſſeſſed of <hi>Popaea.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vitellius.</note> For <hi>Vitellius</hi> let <hi>Iupiter</hi> looke his cheere bee good, or elſe his pallate will purſe his hoſt: <hi>Galba</hi> ſhewes the difference betweene opinion and tryall, and withall that there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:178005:30"/> enemy to praiſe then expectation: <hi>Otho,</hi> that it is not impoſſible to poſſeſſe great places for vilde cauſes: <hi>Vitellius</hi> that there is nothing that diſcouers a laſciuious mind ſo cleerely, as power and authority. <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Veſpaſian.</note> followes a Prince that <hi>Sylenus</hi> could finde no fault with, but it ſeemes, hee had not read <hi>Dion,</hi> who relates the time of his whores death:<note place="margin">Giuen to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> heere is the oddes of beeing neere an Emperour, for a thouſand better deſeruing women died in thoſe times without mention: he ſaith he delighted much in her, neither becomming his age, office, nor wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but I find none without ſome ayle or other.</p>
               <p>It had been a good time for <hi>Sylenus,</hi> to haue asked this, what it was he repented him of, whether it were his louing his brothers wife to wed, or not, hating his brother inough, or elſe his fearing the people, more then louing <hi>Berenice. Domitian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Domitian. His cruelty.</note> had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a butchers ſhop then a palace: for there it could hardly haue been ſayd of him, <hi>Solus est, ne muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca quidem cum eo:</hi> now <hi>Traiane</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Traiane.</note> appeares, vpon whoſe ſight,<note place="margin">Giuen to drink.</note> 
                  <hi>Sylenus</hi> giues <hi>Iupiter</hi> warning to looke to <hi>Gani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes:</hi> hee might alſo haue bidden him be carefull of his <hi>Nectar;</hi> for he loued his lector as wel as boies. The graue fellow following muſt be in <hi>Aurelius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aurelius.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my geſſe a fellow meeter to haue made a priuate man then a Prince,<note place="margin">Too milde.</note> one of his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons was his ſufferance: a good pretty prayſe for a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but nothing fit for a Prince, he was alſo pitifull, a procurer of loue: but what of that, loue thus obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is too familiar a Vertue for an Emperour. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinax</hi> bought his regalitie at a deare rate, his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fault was his ill husbandry, for as trees in their firſt growth are defended by bryars, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:178005:31"/> vncut vp, ouerthrow the floriſhing of the tree; ſo an vnlawfull elected Prince, ſeldome eſcapes plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe, by thoſe that ſet him vp; for couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being the cauſe of their combination, nothing can ſerue their vnſatiable deſires, nor be thought a ſufficient recompence: aske <hi>Laetus</hi> els by the fortune of <hi>Plautianus.</hi> Here comes <hi>Seuerus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seuerus.</note> a Prince of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent worthineſſe, had not his vertue ſuffered ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke by his affections,<note place="margin">Too affectionate to his children.</note> 
                  <hi>erant ei filii multo chariores quam ciues,</hi> which though a priuate man may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, whoſe gouernment is but a houſhold, it is a ſhame for a Prince, whoſe office as it reſembles the gods in power, ſo ſhould it in being free from partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Macrinus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Macrinus.</note> entreth: a thing made by chance, and ouerthrowne by chance,<note place="margin">Improuident.</note> come from a baſe Progeny, and ruined by an infant. Alas, for this poore fellow that followes; <hi>Alexander</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alexander.</note> that dyed becauſe he loued his Parents well; this is he that would giue any mony for quietnes,<note place="margin">Giuen too much to peace.</note> and made Oratours the ſupporters of his Empire. <hi>Debere vnumquem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuis fortunis acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcere,</hi> a ſpeech fit for a warme chamber, and no bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, queſtionleſſe he ſought not the Empire, but the Empire him: ſo doe the Fates or chance, or if you will, more high and certaine powers conſtitute ignorant men in high places, to diſtemper all, to giue after the more grace to the reorderer. There follows more, but I will not follow all, nor ſtand vpon the Authors Poetry, or by-ſpeeches, I write vpon him, not him out, they that will haue it more orderly, were beſt goe thither for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:31"/>
               <head>Compariſon betweene <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw to the compariſon betweene <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar: Caeſar</hi> loued a wench, as well as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> wine, both faults, but which moſt dangerous diſputable, they both impaire the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the one with laying too much vpon the head, the other with taking too much from the head: wine drownes reaſon, luſt prefers his wench before the World: in wine <hi>Alexander</hi> killed <hi>Clytus, Caeſar</hi> proclaimes loue letters in the Senate: both brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches likely to waſte authority, but which of them moſt dangerous, I leaue to the cenſurers, both of them doubtleſſe full of danger, for they are the priuy gates, whereat Conſpirators get entrance. More ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did <hi>Alexander</hi> begin to buſie fame, but that was his fortune. <hi>Caeſar</hi> more worthily, if not at laſt vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for, hee ouerthrew the hinderance of a meane ſtate, and made way through the obſcurity of his birth, which he confeſſeth difficult. <hi>Difficilius ſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem ciuitatis a primo ordine in ſecundum, quam a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo in nouiſsimum detrudi;</hi> how he did this deſerues note: I find all his actions, euen his youngeſt, to be carried with great maieſty, and an intent to lay the foundation of a reuerend opinion of him in the harts of men; his behauiour amongſt the Pirats was one, the refuſing the friendſhip of <hi>Lepidus</hi> another, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the author of reſtoring the Tribunes office: theſe for example, vpon which time will not ſuffer me to worke my will, the wiſe obſeruer may for me, and gaine by it. <hi>Alexander</hi> was not idle in his childs age,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:32"/> his managing <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> argued courage; his vſe of Embaſſadors, wiſedome; the denying to run without Kings, maieſtie: but theſe were beautified with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the actions of a Prince, for they would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Caeſar</hi> halfe ſo well, becauſe a priuate man; that <hi>Caeſar</hi> wept at the ſight of <hi>Alexanders</hi> picture, is no aduantage, for he had the ods of him by birth: then both were happy, in not hauing the firſt growth of their indeuours, ouer-driped by men already great; <hi>Greece</hi> at this time, not hauing any great Souldier. <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his firſt Conſulſhip, being matched with a heauy fellow, that not able to keep way with his ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſtrength of his ſpirit, gaue him leaue to manage all matters alone, whereupon his two names ſerued for the names of both the Conſuls, <hi>Nonnulli vrbanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum quid per iocum testandi gratia ſignarent, non Caeſare &amp; Bibulo, ſed Iulio &amp; Caeſare Conſule actum ſcriberent:</hi> they tried how the world would like their authorities, by two different meanes. <hi>Alexander</hi> an abſolute Prince inuaded <hi>Greece,</hi> by which hee made them vnderſtand that his youth deſerued not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and brought them to be aſſiſtants in the wars againſt <hi>Perſia. Caeſar</hi> lower, but no leſſe politikely, he tooke the occaſion of his daughters death, and in an office of affection preſented the people with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and nouelties: <hi>munus populo aepulum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pronuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit in filiae memoriam, quod ante eum nemo fecit;</hi> this was a taſte of their likings, a loue letter of an Amoriſt, which if taken, more wil be taken: <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſeems in the difficulty of their conqueſts the worthier, no nation of <hi>Alexanders</hi> being comparable, either to the <hi>Gaules</hi> or <hi>Heluetians,</hi> but in the vpſhot alike, both the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an &amp; <hi>Pompey</hi> being greater in reputation then truth:
<pb facs="tcp:178005:32"/> they did well, as long as they went with the tyde: it was the generation long before ſpent, that made the Perſian diademe ſhine with Imperiall title, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of neceſſity, that is wont to moue magnanimity, was taken away, and now left an ouerflowing of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which makes men degenerate and become ſlothfull. <hi>Pompey</hi> became great by the trauels of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus</hi> and others; neither his managing the ciuil wars was as it ſhould be, nor his aduerſity rightly mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ſo that, me thinks, beholding him, I behold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a bubble of fortunes: for their particular valours, they were both valiant, in their military diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, they differed, which might be by the difference of their aduerſaries, nature and country: in the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall point of Armes they agreed, to encounter the hearts of men, as well as bodies. Therfore did <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> deny <hi>Parmenio</hi> the inuading his enemies by night, anſwering the conqueſts of their hearts gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, not of a particular army was the way: the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>Perſia</hi> being aboundant in men, could neuer haue bin ouercome, if their diſcourſe could haue laid the <hi>Macedonian</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſts vpon any accident, but then vanquiſhed, when feare ſhould make them ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adde, to the valour of their enemies, and think baſely of their owne ſtrengths: not thus, but to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Caeſar</hi> neuer miſliked the multitude of his enemies, difficulty being euer a ſpurre to his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That humor that <hi>Caeſar</hi> poſſeſt his Souldiers with, at the ſcorning life at the hands of <hi>Caeſars</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I find not in <hi>Alexanders,</hi> yet had he one of the chiefe inſtigators, the being ſtil a Conqueror; for had <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſometimes loſt, they would haue growne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. This branch came firſt from the root of ſucceſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:33"/> ſeconded by ſome gallant ſpirits of <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſide, emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by their followers, rewarded by <hi>Caeſar;</hi> both held the hearts of the ſouldiers by liberality, the onely meanes to make them apt for great matters, and his meanes that attempts great matters, that which wee call the common good, this is a chiefe limbe of, the ingroſſing which alienates the harts of ſubiects more then any thing, and with thoſe natures that muſt feele the effects of vertue, with their hand: no doubt libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality makes them daring, the contrary, Cowards: <hi>Alexander</hi> maintained this honeſteſt, thankes to his Patrimony: for a ſpirit that aimes at ſo great matters, cannot determine thoſe things diſhoneſt that are any thing auaileable. <hi>Suetonius</hi> ſayth of <hi>Caeſar, Vrbes diru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſaepius ob praedam quam delictum,</hi> an impardonable fault, for though fury, ſmart, or rapine may carry the common Souldier paſt the bounds of reaſon; yet ſhould the Generals minde be ſtill one, and behold nothing with ſo much loue as iuſtice, but this was the violence of Ambition, who dares diſpleaſe right, then her aſſiſtants. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> after his victories, vſed to giue his ſouldiers an accuſtomed liberty, a preſident for all the ſucceſſe dangerous, for of all rewards and incouragements, libertie is the moſt dangerous to the giuer. Contrariwiſe, <hi>Alexander</hi> then curbed his Souldiers, doubting inſolency, the deſtinate diſeaſe of ſucceſſe, which he did by giuing education to the Perſian youth, and after imploying them, a deſigne full of wiſedome, for his conqueſts hauing layd all things at her feete, they had no need of his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but hee of their loyalties, which had they found, and found before his poſſeſſion of other ſtrengths, doubtleſſe they would haue made him their ſlaue,
<pb facs="tcp:178005:33"/> that counted himſelfe Monarch of the World: but this I find it diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious, to rely vpon one aſſiſtant, for two are not ſo likely to fayle as one; and to ſay truth, both will be the more true, becauſe they are two. Equally did they ſubiect their bodies to rayſe their reputations, they knew the force of example, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned appetite for honours ſake. <hi>Alexander</hi> would not adde to the thirſt of his companions, with the quenching of his owne. <hi>Caeſar</hi> in a ſtraight lodging gaue his friends the houſe, and lay himſelf in the ayre; I cannot ſay in the cold, for he that is wrapt in the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thoughts of ambition, cannot feele heate nor cold, nor any of theſe diſtemperatures: it is idleneſſe that betraies vs to the opinion of aches and infirmities; for he that imploies his minde, carrieth his body about without feeling the burthen: the vſe of theſe is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent remedy againſt enuy, meane fortunes thinking greatneſſe, loues greatneſſe to nouriſh delicacy; but this is diſproued by partaking with their extremities. Both intertained a ſweetneſſe of nature in bewayling the miſery or death of their enemies, which, whether it came from the grounds of clemency, or otherwiſe to wrap ſome other purpoſe in, is hardly to be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for there is no ſuch counterfaiter to the life, as an aſpiring diſpoſition: Thus <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſate vp the ſtatues of <hi>Silla</hi> and <hi>Pompey;</hi> thus <hi>Alexander</hi> kindly and honeſtly entertained the wife and mother of <hi>Darius: Caeſar</hi> took to mercy the relikes of <hi>Pompeys</hi> ouerthrowne Army: <hi>Alexander</hi> ſuffered the mother of <hi>Darius</hi> to ſolemnize the burials of his ſlaine enemies, which compaſſion is the onely balme to heale vp the wound of reuenge. Laſtly, <hi>Caeſar</hi> wept at the ſight of <hi>Pompeys</hi> head: and <hi>Alexander</hi> ſharply executed the murtherer of <hi>Darius;</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178005:34"/> In the firſt, I ſee how pretily diſſimulation can apply her ſelfe ſometimes; for ſurely <hi>Caeſar</hi> felt no remorſe in the hardneſſe of his labours, ſuch thoughts attend decay'd eſtates, not the ſummer of fortune. In the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one death ſerues two turnes, for death rewarded him, and death mitigated the rancor, likely to ſpring out of the aſhes of <hi>Darius.</hi> About conſpiracies, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> ſpake as <hi>Caeſar</hi> thought, <hi>Satius eſt, alieno me mori ſcelere, quam metu meo,</hi> they might haue liued longer, if they had been of another minde; yet I thinke they choſe well, for they choſe the eaſieſt: for feare runnes diuiſion vpon death, euery thought being an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of torment, at the end they meete in the laſt courſe of greatneſſe: <hi>Alexander</hi> was a King, and would needs be a god: <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe not a King, a King; thus doe the baits of fortune coozen vs, and ſtuffe vs with monſtrous and vnnatural thoughts; they dyed both violent deaths, the end of violent ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for who miſlikes not that one ſhould poſſeſſe ſo much of honour, fame and dominion as would ſerue many?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octauius</hi> comes againe, whoſe beginning to ſpeake, reſembles his life, buſie in the ſeparating enuy and greatneſſe, which he did by giuing euery ſtate a taſte of his gouernment: by turnes they felt it all, euen the meaneſt and youngeſt, the ſureſt ſtrengthener of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: only this Prince gaue occaſion leaue to chuſe, which was to be entertained of peace or warres: an excellent temper, the which many of his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors and Succeſſors had loſt by, whiles they regarded not which was moſt fit for their Countries, but which was moſt fitting their natures: it were too long to touch all the particulars of his life; let it ſuffice, they
<pb facs="tcp:178005:34"/> all tended to ſettle the troubled eſtate of his time, the teſtimonies of diſhonour that the Romanes ſuffered vnder <hi>Craſſus</hi> and <hi>Anthonie,</hi> by the hands of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, he ſolued, as much as the reſtoring the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ornaments, areſted by the Victors might, which witneſſeth wiſedome is a more preuailing aſſiſter then ſtrength; hee enforced all the Knights of Rome, to yeeld an account of their liues, an ordinance, looke on which ſide you will, full of health, for idleneſſe brings barrenneſſe; his Epiſtle to his adopted ſonne illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates another l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbe of his wiſedome: <hi>Noli in hac re nimium indignari, quenquam eſſe qui de me male loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe ill ſpeakers are rather troubleſome then dangerous, an humour ariſing rather out of ſome light paſſion or wanton gadding of the tongue, then from malice; who is more ſilent, more full of poyſon; ouer thoſe care, but ouer the other, neglect is the beſt medicine: he refuſed the name of <hi>Dictator,</hi> though his authority farre exceeded it, the onely courſe to make greatneſſe ſtand firmely; for by the common eye, names are more plainely ſeene, then executions, which ſilently enioy a more ample and ſafe rule, then thoſe that make their titles march before their power. Our Dialoguiſt omits ſome, and I ſome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Traiane</hi> ſpeakes next, a Prince full of merits; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in his warlike actions, but me thinkes it was to the ſame end, that he made warre vpon a Country: <hi>ſed reuera id bellum ſuſcepit adductus gloriae cupiditate;</hi> it often falls out thus, and as often that our diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons without any great paines giue vs pretty graces: therefore ſay I, a young man not couetous, and an olde man no lecher, deſerues neither thanks nor mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, but their exchange doth well, come they from
<pb facs="tcp:178005:35"/> what cauſe they will, they are well; he was an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince, and that title his ſubiects gaue him, <hi>opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cognominatus eſt,</hi> he deſerued it for he abſtained as much from depriuing his ſubiects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their goods, as from vnlawfull ſlaughters, both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the maine vertues of a Prince, for to pill them, is no leſſe horrible, then the tutor of an Infant to betray his charge, the other is bloudy, which though their ieloſies thinke the way of freedome, they are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; for an vniuſt death raiſeth tenne enemies out of one: <hi>Non ei vnquam accidit (quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uenire in huiuſmodi ſolet) vt millites feroces ſe &amp; inſolentes praebuerint,</hi> as great a praiſe as memory can giue a Commander; for nothing is ſo ſure an euidence of a wiſe man, as to bring his ſouldiers to fetch all their determinations from him, and not to let them entertaine inſolency, when victors; nor baſeneſſe, when vanquiſhed; but ſtill to reade his will, and to hold that will a lawe: hee carefully viſited the wounded, honourably buried the dead, marched on foote with them, ſuffered part of their extremities. I like this better then the ſaluting them <hi>commilitones:</hi> ſuffer with them, giue them, care for them; but no fellowes, nor companions; theſe words kill all the actions of greatneſſe, of commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, of pitie, with contempt; for neuer can one man play two parts well, you cannot bee their Iudge and companion; for this equality taketh away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of your ſentence: loue them, but doe not play with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcus</hi> enters, a ſlowe wiſe fellow, whoſe opinion was; <hi>non decere Imperatorem, propere quicquam agere:</hi> I like conſideration well, but not to ſticke faſt vpon a deſigne; ſure he was naturally a dull flegmaticke fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low;
<pb facs="tcp:178005:35"/> and ſo was honeſt whether he would or no, he ſayth little in this Dialogue, and little is ſayd to him; but only he was a wiſe man, becauſe he knew when to ſpeake, and when to hold his peace, which is wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but the loweſt forme of wiſedome: for the higheſt is, when to doe and not to doe. <hi>Post hunc Conſtantium vt diceret, admonuerunt;</hi> vnder this Prince things of note were done; but not by him: thus ſearch the diuine natures into mens actions, the ſtrength of whoſe ſight, is neither to be deceiued, nor corrupted; he rooted out two Tyrants, not hee but himſelfe the firſt, being weake and ſlothfull, two diſeaſes that make the thus diſeaſed, vncapable of great matters; the other, being the impediment of fortune, had the impediment of age, a heauy clogge and the oppoſite to expedition: both of them had both the miſlike of God and men, and would haue ruined themſelues without helpe: he was ſubiect to delicacy and luxury, which being vices vncounter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed with vertue, made him reiected of the gods, and baniſhed into the orbe of the Moone: the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thinkes he enforced not enough how behoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full theſe warres were to the world, rooting out Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, (the curſe of mankinde) where <hi>Caeſar</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made their ambition deſtroy their Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſubuert their Common-wealths; the reſt, or at leaſt many of them, picking quarrels with their neighbours to feed their owne inſatiable appetite: <hi>Si quis ſinus obditus vltra, ſi qua foret tellus quae fuluum mittere aurum, hoſtis erat;</hi> but others faults mend not his, and perhaps it was his enemies that made his quarrell good, for be they neuer ſo worthy, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Princes will finde cauſes to be troubleſome.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178005:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
